<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Britania triumphalis; a brief history of the vvarres and other state-affairs of Great Britain. From the death of the late King, to the dissolution of the last Parliament.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1654</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 202 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 108 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A77548</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B4817A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E1487_2</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R21059</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99869374</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99869374</idno>
            <idno type="VID">170024</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A77548)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 170024)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 191:E1487[2])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Britania triumphalis; a brief history of the vvarres and other state-affairs of Great Britain. From the death of the late King, to the dissolution of the last Parliament.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 207, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Samuel Howes, and are to be sold at at [sic] his shop in Popes-head-Alley.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1654.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Aprill 28:".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Commonwealth and Protectorate, 1649-1660 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History, Military --  Stuarts, 1603-1714 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>Greg Schutz</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>Geremy Carnes</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>Sarah Wingo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>Sarah Wingo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:170024:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Britania Triumphalis;</hi> A BRIEF HISTORY OF THE WARRES AND OTHER STATE-AFFAIRS OF Great Britain.</p>
            <p>From the Death of the late KING, to the Diſſolution of the laſt Parliament.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Vide quam repentè tempus res mutat humanas,</l>
               <l>Tempora mutantur, nos &amp; mutamur in illis.</l>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Samuel Howes,</hi> and are to be ſold at at his Shop in Popes-head-Alley. 1654.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:170024:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:170024:2"/>
            <head>TO THE READER.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Courteous READER,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Here preſent unto thy view a rude and imperfect draught of thoſe notable Occurren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, ſtrange Revolutions, various Contingencies, and wonderfull Tranſmigra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions
<pb facs="tcp:170024:3"/>that have happened in this little corner of the Earth for theſe five years laſt paſt; which although peradventure they may be imbaſed by the courſe and mean allay of this impol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſht dreſſe; yet in this as in all other Histories, you may finde ſome things which may <hi>aut prodeſſe, aut delectare,</hi> either pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit or delight thee: One wiſely and truly calls Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory <hi>the faithfull pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerver of things paſt,
<pb facs="tcp:170024:3"/>and the certain prophet of things to come.</hi> Firſt here is related the Fall of one of the Mightiest Monarchs in <hi>Europe,</hi> and in Him of Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chy it ſelf, with the ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall deſignes and tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actions that were ſet on foot for the inſtating of his Sonne in the Throne, and the fruitleſſe events thereof. The Conqueſt of <hi>Scotland.</hi> The Reducing of <hi>Ireland.</hi> The Revolt of the <hi>Carybe Iſlands,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:170024:4"/>and the Reducing there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of; and of the Iſlands of <hi>Scilly, Jerſey</hi> and <hi>Man.</hi> The Breach between <hi>England</hi> and the <hi>Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Provinces,</hi> and all the memorable Sea-fights that enſued thereupon. The Diſſolution of the (commonly called) ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting Parliament. The Calling another Aſſembly or Parliament, with the manner and cauſe of the diſſolution thereof. The Lord Generall made
<pb facs="tcp:170024:4"/>Lord Protector of the Commonwealth of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> &amp;c. the Solemnities uſed therein, his Recep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and Entertainment in the City of <hi>London;</hi> Other things of leſſe mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment are interwoven and promiſcuouſly mingled up and down the Book, as the nature thereof requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth; all which as to mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and form, I leave to thy impartiall judgement, there to be arraign'd and condemn'd according to
<pb facs="tcp:170024:5"/>the nature of the offence; and withall I requeſt thee, that with patience thou wilt paſſe by ſuch faults as have eſcaped the Preſſe, whether verball, ſyllabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call or literall, and ſo fare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:170024:5"/>
            <head>A Compendious NARRATIVE of the moſt Important Affairs of <hi>Great Britain,</hi> from the Death of the late KING to the Diſſolution of the laſt PARLIAMENT.</head>
            <div n="1-50" type="part">
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S to the externall Cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of the many evils and miſeries where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with this Nation has been afflicted for theſe few years paſt, much might be ſaid, but the chief I have reduc'd to the following Heads.</p>
               <p>The firſt and generall Cauſe was the Sinnes of the People, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> who (ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king a ſurfet of eaſe, plenty and pleaſure) and growing wanton thereby, gaz'd after novelty (that
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:170024:6"/>magneticall attraction of the Ple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beian rout) and as diſcontented with their preſent condition, ſought felicity in things they wanted, and were ſtill unſatisfied even in the accompliſhment thereof:<note place="margin">Malv. Rom.</note> whence is occaſioned the hatred of tranquil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, the deſire of motion, the loa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of preſent things, and ſeeking after future.</p>
               <p>Another principall Cauſe was the lamentable corruptions of the Court, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> not inferior in vice to the moſt infamous Court in Europe, not excelling in any thing that might be called virtuous, but inur'd themſelves to a ſoft and luxurious life, abounding in all manner of voluptuous and effeminate plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, rejecting the more noble di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctates of nature and grace, not at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chieving any one enterpriſe, that might render them either feared abroad or loved at home: but ſtill wanting fuell for the fire of their
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:170024:6"/>prodigality, daily invented ſome new and indirect courſes and wayes to torment the people; whoſe jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſies and fears encreaſing with their grievances, brought forth a moſt bloudy inteſtine warre, which ended not but in the ſubverſion of Church and State, as then eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, <hi>viz.</hi> Epiſcopacy and Monarchy, the Head of both being cut off and the Bodies diſcomfited. And though the King was judged to be the Patron of thoſe many innova<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and miſcarriages that befell the Church and Commonwealth, yet I am fully perſwaded they pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded not from the depravedneſſe of his will, but the flexibility of his nature, overwhelm'd by his per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicious Councell, by which he ſeem'd of a leſſer magnitude then otherwiſe he would have done; yet was he not the worſt although the moſt unfortunate of Princes: and in him ended Monarchy, but
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:170024:7"/>not the miſeries of theſe Nations: for after ſome years civil (and yet unnaturall) warre betwixt King and Parliament, they at length ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minated in the vanquiſhing of his Armies, the ſurpriſall, captivity and death of his Perſon, upon a ſcaffold before his Palace of White-Hall, <hi>Jan.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>0<hi rend="sup">th</hi> 1648.</p>
               <p>The third and laſt Cauſe which I ſhall mention (though not the leaſt, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> was the Pride, Avarice, Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bition and ſlothfulneſſe of the Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy, who not only ſtarv'd their flocks by withholding the ſpirituall food of their ſouls, but alſo tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented their bodies, by exhauſting and ſucking their bodily ſubſtance, inſomuch that the Nation groaned under the burden of their abomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable corruptions, who ſhould have been the examples and leading-cards of piety and ſanctity: yet did the popular fury contribute more to the confuſion of their Hierarchy,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:170024:7"/>then all their Crimes put together; nor were they cry'd down with more heat, then afterwards cry'd up, verifying that of the Poet,
<q>
                     <l>Quid populi tibi voce places?<note place="margin">Mori E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pigr.</note> ſaepe op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tima caecus,</l>
                     <l>Dat vitio, &amp; temerè deteriora probat.</l>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>Having now hinted out unto you the Cauſes of our Warres and the diſtractions that follow'd (the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning, progreſſe and concluſion thereof, to the beheading of the King, being accurately and briefly deſcribed by another hand) I ſhall proceed to that which remains.<note place="margin">May's Brev.</note>
               </p>
               <p>No ſooner was this mighty Prince bereaved of his life and dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity in ſuch ſort as is before related, but Monarchy (the darling of the multitude) was voted chargeable, unneceſſary and uſeleſſe, and the Government was reſolv'd into that of a Commonwealth.</p>
               <p>Yet this mutation happened not
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:170024:8"/>for want of ſuch as by a lineall deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent, and according to the uſage of this Nation, might pretend a Title to the Crown: for there was a plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifull Iſſue of the late King (both Male and Female) then ſurviving, but from ſome other politicall rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons beſt known to the then ſway<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Powers, the which added and mi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iſtred hopes equall to the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>contents of the people.</p>
               <p>Now <hi>Charles</hi> (though eldeſt Sonne of the late King) inherited little ſave the misfortunes of his Father, and what elſe he could chaulk out with his Sword; yet his g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ateſt hopes and expectations were from <hi>Ireland</hi> where the ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall factions <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>, proclaim'd him King, and bent their whole ſtrength againſt the Intereſt of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealth of <hi>England;</hi> and in ſhort ſpace become ſo formidable, and prevail'd ſo much, that they poſſeſt all the ſtrong holds of that
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:170024:8"/>Country (<hi>Dublin</hi> and <hi>Londonderry</hi> excepted) both which were ſtrait<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly beſieg'd, the former by an Army of 22000. men under the Marq. of <hi>Ormond,</hi> the latter by a party of the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Rebels: he had likewiſe adjoyning to the territories of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> the Iſlands of <hi>Scilly, Jerſey</hi> and <hi>Man,</hi> which yet advantag'd him no more then by nouriſhing a few ſmall Picaroons to infeſt the nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row ſeas.</p>
               <p>But his affairs in <hi>Ireland</hi> were no ſooner at this height, but they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gun as ſuddenly to decline; for there being about 3000. Horſe and Foot ſafely landed at <hi>Dublin</hi> (as the forlorne of a greater body) they were join'd with what other Forces they could then make, all which made not above 9000. at the ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt, and commanded by the va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liant and never to be forgotten Coll. <hi>Mich. Jones,</hi> ſallied forth, and not only rais'd the ſiege, but routed
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:170024:9"/>the whole Army of the Marq. of <hi>Ormond,</hi> himſelf hardly eſcaping, about 2000. were ſlain in the place and in the purſuit, ſome thouſands were taken Priſoners, as likewiſe all their Ordinance, Ammunition, Carriages, Proviſion, with great ſtore of rich Booty. To adde to their declining ſtate, and help for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward the deſtruction of theſe grand confaederates, who were thus de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feated in the midſt of their mighty Attempts and huge imaginations, <hi>Oliver Cromwell</hi> Lord Deputy of <hi>Ireland</hi> landed at <hi>Dublin</hi> with a powerfull Army (about the midſt of <hi>Aug.</hi> 1649.) well accommoda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted for the accompliſhment of that enterpriſe ſo happily began.<note place="margin">Generall <hi>Cromwall</hi> landed in <hi>Ireland Aug.</hi> 1649</note> And firſt he laid ſiege to <hi>Drogheda,</hi> and in ſmall time (though with ſome difficulty and loſſe) took it by ſtorm; and that he might chaſtiſe their obſtinacy, and ſtrike terror in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to other Garriſons, put to the
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:170024:9"/>ſword all that were found in Armes, which were about 3000. preſently after which there fell into his hands many other Garriſons, ſome by force, others by ſur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>nder, <hi>viz, Trim, Dundalke,</hi> the <hi>Nur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>x<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ord, Roſſe, Bandonbridge, Kingſale, P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſſage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort,</hi> with many more <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>edious to relate. In other parts of <hi>Ireland,</hi> ſeverall Garriſons of the Enemy were taken, and many conſiderable Parties were routed by others of the Parliament<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tains, <hi>viz.</hi> the Lord <hi>Broghill,</hi> S<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Charles Coot,</hi> Coll. <hi>Vena<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>les,</hi> Coll. <hi>Jones</hi> and others; and though this People have been ſtill on the loſing hand, yet have they held out in Boggs and f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſtneſſes even to this day; whereby we ſee, that the vanquiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing this Nation, was not ſo feaſible as in the dayes of <hi>Henry</hi> the ſecond, who made it but a winters work to reduce and ſubject the people there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of: A thing ſcarce credible (ſayes
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:170024:10"/>our Author) that a Country ſo populous,<note place="margin">Dan. Chro.</note> a Nation of that diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition, ſhould not lift up a hand to defend it ſelf! But it ſeems (ſaith he) they were wholly unacquaint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with ſuch ſtrange kind of fights, or ſuch weapons; inſomuch that the terror thereof laid them pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate to the overrunner; but though the winning of that Nation was accompliſht with ſo much eaſe, yet in the keeping thereof was more difficulty and coſt. In ſhort, The Affairs of the Catholick and other their confederate party moulder'd and declin'd more and more, to the great grief and diſheartning of the Royall Party.</p>
               <p>Much about this time hapned a generall defection of the Engliſh Plantations from their obedience to the Parliament,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Virginia</hi> and the <hi>Carybe</hi> Iſlands revolt.</note> 
                  <hi>viz. Virginia</hi> and the <hi>Carybe</hi> Iſlands: Where, in the ardency of Popular fury, Litur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy and Monarchy were cry'd up,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:170024:10"/>and the Nonconformiſts were ſome ſtigmatiz'd, ſome fin'd, and ſome baniſh'd; which courſes procur'd them no ſmall trouble and loſſe, in the decay of their Trade and loſſe of their Ships, all Nations being prohibited from trading or traffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quing with them upon pain of for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feiture: All which were in a few moneths reduc'd by a Fleet of Ships from <hi>England,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duc'd.</note> under S<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>George Ayſcue,</hi> not being able to ſubſiſt for any conſiderable ſpace of time without Trade.</p>
               <p>The Engliſh coaſts were like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe miſerably infeſted with Py<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rates from <hi>Scilly, Jerſey, Ireland</hi> and <hi>France;</hi> but the very Prince of Pyrates and Plunderers, was one commonly known by the Name of Prince <hi>Rupert,</hi> who with the rem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of that Fleet, that (not long before) had revolted from the Commonwealth of <hi>England,</hi> being about nine tall and warlike Ships,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:170024:11"/>committed many ſpoyles and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>praedations, not only upon the Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh coaſts, but in other places like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, whereby the Merchants incur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red no ſmall loſſe.</p>
               <p>Now for encouraging of Trade and reducing of Pyrates, a ſtout and luſty Fleet of Ships well rig'd and man'd were ſet forth, which (with Gods bleſſing) ſcour'd the channel and blockt up Prince <hi>Rupert</hi> in the Harbour of <hi>Kingſale,</hi> which with the Town being taken by the Lord Gen. <hi>Cromwell,</hi> they were forc't thence to make all the ſaile they could away (leaving about 3 Ships behind) and at length arriv'd at <hi>Lizbon,</hi> the Imperiall City of the King of <hi>Portugall,</hi> and crav'd his protection, which was not deny'd them, the which caus'd much trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, loſſe and detriment to that King; and was the only cauſe of that unhappy difference that fell out between him and this Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealth
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:170024:11"/>as hereafter will ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear.</p>
               <p>Other Deſigns were ſet on foot by the Royall party, for the obtain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their ends.</p>
               <p>The firſt was the Commiſſiona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of <hi>James Graham</hi> Earl of <hi>Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troſe,</hi> for the raiſing what Forces he could in <hi>Holland</hi> and other parts to invade <hi>Scotland.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The ſecond was the procuring a Treaty between the <hi>Scots</hi> and their King, whereby they might by force or fraud work him into an abſolute Soveraignty over that Nation, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king good that known diſtich,</p>
               <q>
                  <l>If the Lyons skin will not prevaile,</l>
                  <l>They'l piece it with the Foxes taile.</l>
               </q>
               <p>To give more life to theſe un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertakings, Ambaſſadors were diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patcht to <hi>Spain, Italy, Denmarke, Sweden, Ruſsia, Turky,</hi> &amp;c. in the Name of <hi>Charles</hi> the Second, King of <hi>Great Britaine, France</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi>
                  <pb n="14" facs="tcp:170024:12"/>Defender of the Faith, which Title (with much confidence) he aſſumed to himſelf, yet obtain'd neither Men nor Monies worth noting from any of them, but excuſes, pleas and complements in abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance; for alas they had rather he ſhould not be at all, then be too great: they, that have equall dignity of birth, had rather have no equall then any ſuperior.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Montroſe</hi> (according to his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters Inſtructions,<note place="margin">Montroſe <hi>enters</hi> Scotland,</note> having got toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſome inconſiderable ſupplies of Men and Monies) at length lands in the North of <hi>Scotland,</hi> where he had not long been, ere he was aſſailed and routed by a party from the Kirk,<note place="margin">is routed, taken pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoner and executed.</note> and his Perſon brought priſoner in moſt diſgrace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full manner to the Caſtle of <hi>Edin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burgh,</hi> where to fill up the meaſure of their malice, they hang'd him ten yards from the ground, an act ſo barbarous and inhumane, as ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mits
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:170024:12"/>of no compariſon: thus liv'd and thus dy'd the Mirrour of Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood and Map of Miſery, who for many years together had been a thorne in the ſide of the Kirk; wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe the ſeverall defeats he gave them, and who from ſmall begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings accompliſht vaſt enterpriſes, whoſe hard fate it was at laſt to fall into their bloudy hands, <hi>Sic tranſit gloria mundi.</hi> One would have thought this one act of theirs had been of force enough to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent all future overtures between the <hi>Scots</hi> and their declared King: Yet as if he had throughly learnt that leſſon, <hi>Qui neſcit diſsimulare neſcit regnare,</hi> he took little notice thereof.</p>
               <p>Next <hi>Montroſe</hi> was executed Sir <hi>John Urrey,</hi> Coll. <hi>Spotſwood,</hi> and others that were the chief actors in that undertaking, by which meanes they were rid of a dangerous e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemy.</p>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:170024:13"/>
               <p>On all this the Engliſh (like cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telous ſtatiſts) had a watchful eye, and on every of thoſe actings, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther open or ſecret, that might have any reflection upon them or their affairs: and to the end they might the better ſound the contriva<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ces of their adverſaries, they endeavour to ſtrengthen themſelves by for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign Alliance; and accordingly they ſent D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Doriſlaus</hi> a wiſe and knowing man as publike Agent,<note place="margin">D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                     <hi>Doriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laus</hi> mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther at the <hi>Hague.</hi>
                  </note> into the United Provinces, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by to keep a right underſtanding and fair correſpondency between the two Republikes: where he had not long been ere he was ſlain by ſix aſſaſſinates that broke into his lodgings at the <hi>Hague</hi> in a diſguiſed habit, by which meanes they eſca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped unpuniſhed, notwithſtanding the many endeavours (at leaſt pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendedly uſed) for their apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion. The authors of this Tragedy were afterwards known to be Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:170024:13"/>Cavaliers, diſcontented at their declining ſtate, and loſſe of their old Maſter: one whereof was Col. <hi>Spotſwood</hi> aforementioned, who at his death confeſt he was an actor therein. Thus ſtood the Engliſh affairs in reference to their enemies abroad, while they were in ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what worſe plight at home: for a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>midſt the ſeverall factions that ſprung up during theſe late warres, none was more deſperate then that commonly known by the name of Levellers,<note place="margin">The Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vellers mutiny.</note> who at once ſo wrought with the Souldiery, that a conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable party of Horſe withdrew themſelves from the Army, and gathered together ſuch others of their party as they could conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niently, thinking thereby to force their Lords and Maſters to ſuch things as their immature and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bridled apprehenſions had dictated to them:<note place="margin">are ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſt,</note> But by the care and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duſtry of Gen. <hi>Fairfax,</hi> they were
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:170024:14"/>defeated at a place called <hi>Burford</hi> in <hi>Oxfordſhire,</hi> and of thoſe that were taken, ſome were made ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>emplary, others were caſhiered the Army, and the reſt upon their ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion were taken into favour.</p>
               <p>Not long after was brought to tryall at the <hi>Guildhall London,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Lilburne <hi>tri'd at</hi> Guild-hall</note> the grand Champion, the chiefeſt and only Patriot of the faction afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid, <hi>viz. John Lilburne,</hi> a man of a reſtleſſe and yet invincible ſpirit, that could never be deter'd with threats or won with favours, by a ſpeciall Commiſſion of <hi>Oyer</hi> and <hi>Terminer;</hi> where was preſent moſt of the Judges and Juſtices of the ſeverall Courts at <hi>Westminster,</hi> the Lord Mayor, Sheriffs, and ſeverall Aldermen of <hi>London,</hi> with others of eminent quality. The Indictment with many crimes of a treaſonable nature, as being the Author of ſuch and ſuch Books mentioned therein; which Books were fraught with
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:170024:14"/>the moſt ſhamefull revilings, ſcur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rilous invectives, and malicious outcries againſt the Governours and Government of the Nation, that the heart of man could invent, calling them Tyrants, Traytors, Conquering Uſurpers, and what not. Now though nothing was more generally beleeved, then that the Books aforeſaid were of his own penning and publiſhing, yet at his tryall he made ſuch an excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent,<note place="margin">is clear'd and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leaſed.</note> ſubtle and ſingular defence, that the Jury brought him in Not guilty, whereupon he had his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leaſe.</p>
               <p>By this time the ſeverall tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actions that were between the <hi>Scots</hi> and their King, had brought forth a Treaty at <hi>Breda</hi> in the <hi>Netherlands,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the <hi>Scots</hi> and their <hi>King</hi> concluded</note> a Town of ſpeciall note belonging to the Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> at whoſe coſt and charges it was both con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued and concluded: Now that part of the Agreement that had the
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:170024:15"/>moſt eſpeciall influence on us, was, that they ſhould endeavour to the utmoſt of their power, to reinſtate him in his Fathers Throne, inveſt him in his Power and Greatneſſe, and eſtabliſh him in his juſt Rights and Dignities: where we ſhall at preſent leave him, to ſee how the Affairs of his Adverſaries the Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh ſucceeded.</p>
               <p>The differences that lately broke out between the King of <hi>Portugall</hi> and this Nation, were now widened by acts of open hoſtility; for when the Engliſh perceiv'd, that neither intreaties nor threats would make him force Prince <hi>Rupert</hi> out of his Harbour, and that the often appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations and negotiations of the Engliſh Agent M. <hi>Charles Vane,</hi> in order thereunto, could availe no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, but on the contrary prepar'd what Ships of warre he had to joyn with <hi>Rupert,</hi> and ſo to chaſe the Engliſh from his Coaſts, they ſeiz'd
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:170024:15"/>many of his Ships richly laden both inward and outward bound: but the King doubting his ſtrength, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſted from falling upon the Engliſh Fleet, and fell to ſeize the eſtates, and ſecure the perſons of the Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants and Factors reſiding in <hi>Liſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bon</hi> and other places under his Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſdiction.</p>
               <p>About this time likewiſe the Engliſh ſent an Agent to the King of <hi>Spain,</hi> viz. M. <hi>Anth. Aſhcam,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">M. <hi>Aſhcam</hi> the Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh Agent murther'd at <hi>Madrid.</hi>
                  </note> a moſt learned and excellently well accompliſht Gentleman, who on the 5<hi rend="sup">th</hi> of <hi>June</hi> 1650. landed at <hi>Santa Maria,</hi> where (hearing of many threats againſt his perſon) he procur'd a Guard that conducted him to <hi>Madrid,</hi> where is kept the Court of the King of <hi>Spain:</hi> The firſt night it was his hard fortune to lie at an Inne; the next day while with his Interpreter Signior <hi>Riba</hi> he ſate at dinner, ſix divels in the ſhapes of men, knockt at the door,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:170024:16"/>had eaſie acceſſe, and being entred M. <hi>Aſhcam</hi> roſe to ſalute them, whereupon the foremoſt ſtab'd him in the head, and his Interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter endeavouring to eſcape was ſtab'd in the belly, both falling down dead in the place. Whence the murtherers fled to the <hi>Venetian</hi> Ambaſſadors houſe, but were de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied entrance: whence they fled to the Sanctuary, were purſued and carried to priſon from thence by the Kings ſpeciall command, one of them only eſcaping. Hereupon a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roſe a great difference between the King and the Church, about the violation of the holy Sanctuary, and thereby infringing the Sacred Rights and Priviledges of the Church, and demanded that the Aſſaſinates ſhould be delivered a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain into the Sanctuary. On the other hand, the Parliament of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> by ſundry Meſſages, earneſtly preſt that Juſtice might be ſeverely
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:170024:16"/>inflicted upon thoſe execrable of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenders, that had perpetrated ſo hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rid and vile an act upon their pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like Miniſter. And indeed it was a crime of ſo tranſcendent a nature, that me thinks it ſhould not enter into the heart of any conſiderate man to imagin of any expiation for them here, however it may pleaſe God to deal with them here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after. The Church notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding prevail'd ſo farre, as to inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt the courſe of Juſtice, for as much as their puniſhment has been hitherto ſuſpended, though for any thing we hear they are yet in du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance.</p>
               <p>Neer this time arrived in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> the Lord <hi>Gerard Scarph,</hi> as Commiſſioner from the States Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinciall of <hi>Holland</hi> and <hi>Weſt Frieſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> and upon the 11<hi rend="sup">th</hi> of <hi>June</hi> 1650. he delivered his Meſſage in Parliament; which though it pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duc'd no more then a mutuall deſire
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:170024:17"/>of an amicable compliance, yet was it very well reſented by the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, that they ſhew'd them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves the leading cards to the reſt of the Provinces at ſuch a time as that.</p>
               <p>Now whenas the Treaty at <hi>Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>da</hi> was fully ended, and that all their Jealouſies and animoſities (not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding the vaſt diſproportion and notable antipathy that was ere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>while between the Royalliſts and Presbyterians) was by this means fully allay'd, at leaſt in ſhew. The <hi>Scots</hi> ſeem'd to want nothing ſave the preſence of their King, wherby to crown their deſires, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>front the Engliſh, in order where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto He haſts from <hi>Breda</hi> to the <hi>Hague,</hi> from thence to <hi>Scheveling,</hi> where he took ſhipping, and at laſt in deſpight of foul weather, and the Engliſh Kingfiſhers that lay there to intercept him, he landed at the <hi>Spey</hi> in the North of <hi>Scotland,</hi> where
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:170024:17"/>he found the greateſt difficulty in aſcending the Throne, and leaſt en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy'd it of any Prince that was ever heard or read of. For upon all oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions he was compeld to trace the ſteps and follow the dictates of that haughty Clergy, in all their fana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick humours and imperious de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crees: who bereav'd him firſt of all his old friends, Counſellors and confederates, whether of the Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy or Layety, who (to ſay the truth) had alwayes accompanied his Father and Him in all their diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſters and dangers; and had ſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wrackt their own fortunes, to carine and repair his, though it may be by this deſertion he intended their reſtauration. But now the <hi>Scots</hi> had a King, yet (as though they had none) they did what ſeem'd right in their own eyes.</p>
               <p>The firſt and moſt pernicious potion they made him to take, and of hardeſt digeſtion, was the <hi>Solemne
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:170024:18"/>League and Covenant,</hi> that <hi>ignis fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuus,</hi> and only ſeminary of bloud and miſchief in theſe three Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</p>
               <p>The next was a Declaration of the Kirks own framing and faſhion<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; wherein he is taught to <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce the ſinnes of his Fathers houſe, and of his own, the Idolatry of his Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, by a conſtant adhering to the Cauſe of God, according to the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, in the firm eſtabliſment of Church-government, as it is laid down in the Directory for publike Worſhip, Confeſsion of Faith and Catechiſme:</hi> This with divers others of the like nature (although with much relu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctancy) he alſo ſigned; which its like burthen'd his ſpirit, yet better'd not his condition, which was like that of a Child under Tutors and Governors; for there was not an Officer in that Church or Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealth, how vile and abject ſoever in place or perſon, but en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy'd
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:170024:18"/>more freedom in body and minde then he. Guarded indeed he was, but little regarded; ſo that move he muſt not but in the ſphaere of the Kirk; they were the <hi>primum mobile,</hi> whereby its apparent that the Government of that Nation was not truly Monarchicall (though they had a King) but Hierarchicall, the confuſion whereof I ſhall now ſet before you.</p>
               <p>The Parliament of <hi>England</hi> weighing right well the condition into which their affairs were now reduc'd (by reaſon of the Agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment that was peec'd up between the <hi>Scots</hi> and their King) after a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious and ſolemne debate, voted that <hi>Thomas</hi> Lord <hi>Fairfax</hi> with the Army under his command ſhould march Northwards: who (after ſome conference had with the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament) and being prompted by an indiſpoſition of body or minde, laid down his Commiſſion: which
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:170024:19"/>was forthwith confer'd upon <hi>Oliver Cromwell</hi> Lord Deputy of <hi>Ireland,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gen. <hi>Fair<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fax</hi> laies down his Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> was pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer'd upon General <hi>Cromwell</hi> Lord De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puty of <hi>Ireland.</hi>
                  </note> who (in order to this Northern ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedition) arriv'd a while after from his victorious atchievements in that country, leaving his Son in Law <hi>Henry</hi> as Lord Deputy in his room.</p>
               <p>Accordingly Orders were iſſued forth for the ſpeedy advance of the Army into <hi>Scotland,</hi> who had no ſooner begun their March, but the <hi>Scots</hi> took the Alarme, and ſent two or three Papers to S<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Arthur Haſlerig</hi> then Governour of <hi>New<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſtle;</hi> wherein they expoſtulated the Caſe about the ſudden ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach of the Engliſh Army, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavouring thereby to impede their march, till ſuch time as their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignes were ripe: alledging (as ſcar-Crowes to fright fooles) the Covenant, the large Treaty and Union between the two Nations, with other circumſtances of the
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:170024:19"/>like nature, as frivolous as they were fruitleſſe.</p>
               <p>The Parliament of <hi>England</hi> then publiſhed likewiſe a Declaration, ſhewing the grounds and reaſons of their Armies advance towards <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> accompanied with another from the Generall and Officers of the Army, ſhewing that that which moov'd them to that great under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taking, was not any reliance upon the arm of fleſh,<note place="margin">The De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration of the Engliſh Army in their march to <hi>Scotland.</hi>
                  </note> or being lifted up with the remembrance of former ſucceſſes, or the deſire of accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhing any deſignes of their own that they had forelaid, but the full aſſurance they had that their Cauſe was juſt in the ſight of God: look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing at the precedent changes, and the ſucceſſes that produc'd them, not as the work of the policy or ſtrength of man, but as the emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent actings of the Providence and Power of God, to bring forth his good will and pleaſure, concerning
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:170024:20"/>the things which he hath determin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the world; adding, That no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing was predominant with them (next to their duty to their duty to God, not to betray a cauſe, to which he had ſo much witneſſed) as the love they had to thoſe that feared God there, who might poſſibly ſuffer through their own miſtakes, or their diſability to diſtinguiſh in a common calamity: of which Chriſtian love they hoped that they gave ſome proof when they were before in <hi>Scotland</hi> with that Army, and were by God made inſtrumentall to break the power of thoſe that oppreſſed the godly Party there; for which (ſay they) their late Engagement to their new King againſt <hi>England</hi> was no good requital, nor their heaping on them the reproach of a Sectarian Army, a Chriſtian dealing: all which (by the grace of God) they could for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get and forgive, and did (as they
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:170024:20"/>ſay) deſire of God that the preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous might be ſeparated from the vile, beginning and concluding with a moſt ſolemn and dreadfull imprecation and appeal; <hi>That to the truth of theſe things the God of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven in his great mercy, pardoning their weakneſses, would judge of them when they came to meet the Enemy in the Field.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This Declaration was ſent by the Generall of the Engliſh Forces from their Head-Quarters at <hi>Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wick</hi> to <hi>Edenburgh</hi> by a Trumpeter, whom they blinded coming and going, what effect this wrought the ſequel of the Story will relate.</p>
               <p>From <hi>Barwick</hi> the Army march<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to the Lord <hi>Mordingtons</hi> Houſe <hi>July</hi> 22. 1650. where they lay three daies: on the 25. they marched to <hi>Copperſpeth,</hi> the 26. to <hi>Dunbar,</hi> where they received ſome proviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons from the Ships ſent on purpoſe to attend the motions of the Army;
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:170024:21"/>foraſmuch as the people of the Countrey had forſook their habita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and had left nothing behinde that might accommodate them. The Army thus refreſht at <hi>Dunbar,</hi> marcht thence to <hi>Haddington:</hi> Next day hearing the Scots would meet them at <hi>Gladſmore,</hi> they la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boured to poſſeſſe the Moor before them, but no conſiderable part ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared, whereupon Major Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall <hi>Lambert</hi> and Collonel <hi>Whalley</hi> men of approved courage with 1400. Horſe were ſent as a Vaunt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guard to <hi>Muſſleborough</hi> to attempt ſomething upon the Enemy if poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble; The General with the reſidue of the Army marching in the rear, the Engliſh and Scotch Horſe had ſome encounters, but the Scots would not endure the Shock: that Night the Engliſh lay encamp'd cloſe at <hi>Muſſleborough;</hi> The Enemy was within four miles of them, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trenched with a Line, flank'd from
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:170024:21"/>
                  <hi>Edenburgh</hi> to <hi>Leith;</hi> the Guns from <hi>Leith</hi> ſcouring moſt parts of the Line, ſo that they lay very ſtrong: The Engliſh finding their Enemies were not eaſily to be at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempted, lay ſtill all that day be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the 20. which proved a ſore day of rain, and greatly diſadvan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tagious to them, having nothing to cover them, all which, expecting a ſpeedy engagement, they did cheerfully undergo it; next day being the 30. the ground very wet, and proviſions being ſcarce, the Engliſh reſolved to draw to their Quarters at <hi>Muſſleborough,</hi> to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſh and re-victuall; which while they were doing the <hi>Scots</hi> fell upon their rear, and put them to ſome diſorder. But ſome bodies of the Engliſh Horſe came forthwith to cloſe with them, which produc'd a hot and gallant skirmiſh, inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much that at length the Engliſh charg'd them ſo home, that they
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:170024:22"/>beat them to their very Trenches. Major General <hi>Lambert</hi> in this diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute was run through the arm with a Lance, and wounded in another part of the body, taken priſoner, but reſcued by Lieutenant <hi>Empſon</hi> of the Generals Regiment; ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall of the Scots were kil'd and ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken Priſoners with ſmall loſſe to the Engliſh: among the reſt there was taken one Lieutenant Colonel, one Major, and ſome Captains, ſome perſons of note were likewiſe ſlain.</p>
               <p>By this means the Engliſh had opportunity to march quietly off to <hi>Muſſleborugh,</hi> which they did that night; but ſo wearied for want of ſleep, and tired with the dirti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the waies, that they ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected the Enemy would make a ſudden infall upon them, which accordingly they did: Between three and four of the Clock next morning, being the 30. of <hi>July,</hi>
                  <pb n="32" facs="tcp:170024:22"/>with 15 ſelect Troops of Horſe un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Command of Major Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral <hi>Montgomery,</hi> and Col. <hi>Straughan,</hi> who came on with great reſolution, beat in the Engliſh Guards, and put a Regiment of Horſe into ſome diſorder; but the Engliſh preſently taking the Alarm charged, routed, purſued, and did execution upon them, within a quarter of a mile of <hi>Edenburgh,</hi> taking and killing ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, as well Officers as Souldiers: the Scotch affairs ſucceeding in this ſort, made them forbear ſuch frequent ſallies, and keep within their intrenchments.</p>
               <p>This was the poſture of the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litary affairs of <hi>Scotland,</hi> when to adde to the miſeries of that peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, all traffique and commerce was prohibited between the two Nations; And ſuch of the <hi>Scots</hi> as had their reſidence in <hi>England,</hi> were commanded to depart the Land within ten daies or therea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bouts;
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:170024:23"/>their Ships (not able to reſiſt, having no Convoy) were often ſurpriz'd by the Engliſh; In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomuch that they were in the road way to ruine: But ſeeing this Moneth of <hi>Auguſt</hi> produced little of Action from the Armies there, it wil not be amiſſe to give a brief account of ſuch remarkable paſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, as about that time hapned in <hi>England</hi> and the Neighbouring Nations.</p>
               <p>At <hi>London</hi> was apprehended, condemned,<note place="margin">Col. <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drews</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>headed at <hi>Tower-hill.</hi>
                  </note> and executed Colonel <hi>Euſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>bius Andrews,</hi> who being taken w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>th a Commiſſion from <hi>Charles Stuart,</hi> and for entring into a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiracy to undermine the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of <hi>England,</hi> ſuffered death as aforeſaid.</p>
               <p>From the United Provinces came accompt of ſome notable tranſactions, which takes as follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth.</p>
               <p>The Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> (Brother
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:170024:23"/>in Law to the <hi>Scots</hi> King, by mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rying his Siſter, Daughter to the late King of <hi>England</hi>) aſpiring to a higher degree of Soveraignty over thoſe Provinces then he or his Predeceſſors ever enjoyed, and being thwarted in ſome of his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects when he was at <hi>Amſterdam,</hi> he thereupon was ſo diſtaſted, that he reſolved to right himſelf, by ſecuring and putting out the leading men in that Province of <hi>Holland,</hi> for which purpoſe he cauſed all the Deputies thereof (being then at the <hi>Hagne</hi>) to aſſembled, which they refuſing, he ſeiz'd moſt of them, thoſe of <hi>Amſterdam,</hi> (whom he chiefly deſir'd) eſcap'd onely. His next deſign was to have ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priz'd the City of <hi>Amſterdam</hi> by a ſtratagem, commanding the Horſe to ſuch a place, under pretence of conducting his Mother, and ſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped his Infantry at <hi>Utrech</hi> in the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary Paſſage-Boats, to come all
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:170024:24"/>night, that they might be there early next morning, and the horſe to have their Rendezvouz upon the Heath between <hi>Naerden</hi> and <hi>Amesford</hi> about midnight, and to be at the Ports of the Town at the moment appointed; By which time the foot ſhould have ſeized on the Regulars, and the S. <hi>Tuni<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s</hi> Ports, and have opened a paſſage for the Horſe to enter; which de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign (if by a wonderfull provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of God in ſending a fierce ſtorm of rain that night, the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended march of the Horſe had not been hindred from coming to the place and time appointed) had in all probability taken effect. Nor had the Town known any thing thereof t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ll too late. But the <hi>Ham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burgh</hi> Poſt, as he was coming to the Town met with ſeverall par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of Horſe, riding to and fro a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout <hi>Amesford</hi> and the Heath, yet who they were he knew not.</p>
               <pb n="39" facs="tcp:170024:24"/>
               <p>Hereof the Lords being inform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, ſtraitway caus'd the Ports to be ſhut, the Bridges drawn, the Guards ſet, the Ordinance plant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and all warlike preparations to be made; and all this while not knowing their enemies. But they were not long in ſuſpence, for no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice was ſoon given, that it was <hi>Count William</hi> with his Forces whoſe deſignments being thus de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feated, the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> accoſts the Town with this following Letter.</p>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <head>Worſhipfull, Prudent, Diſcreet Sirs, and my very good Friends.</head>
                     <p>WHen I was last in the City for the ſervice of the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, I was ſo ſtrangely entertained, that not to be ſubject to the like here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after, I found it expedient to ſend <hi>Count William</hi> with the Troops following him into your City; and ordered him to keep all things in peace and quiet there, that I might not be
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:170024:25"/>hindred by any ill-affected, in ſuch things as yet I have to propound unto you, touching the ſervice of the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, wherein I require your good aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſistance; And in confidence thereof, commending you to the protection of the moſt High, I remain,</p>
                     <closer>
                        <dateline>Hague, <date>
                              <hi>Iuly 29. 1650.</hi>
                           </date>
                        </dateline>
                        <signed>Your Good Friend, <hi>W. Prince of Orange.</hi>
                        </signed>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <p>This ſtratagem (projected with ſo much ſecrecy and ſubtlety) fail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>Count William</hi> drew off his Forces to ſeverall Poſts, with in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent to block up the Town, which being in a poſture of defence, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened their ſluces, and ſet the Land under water round about, and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving ſo done, they ſent a Trum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peter to <hi>Count William</hi> to know the reaſon of that ſo ſudden approach, and to deſire him to retreat with his Army, who returned anſwer, that he could do nothing till he heard from the Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi>
                  <pb n="41" facs="tcp:170024:25"/>yet a little after he thought fit to quit his ſtation and retire; yet the Deputies of <hi>Holland</hi> being faſt in the Caſtle of <hi>Lovenſtaine,</hi> the <hi>Prince of Orange</hi> had the advantage of making his own conditions which were theſe.</p>
               <p n="1">1. That the Town of <hi>Amſter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam</hi> ſhall agree with the other ſix Provinces for continuing the <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litia,</hi> as it is now ſetled for four or five years.</p>
               <p n="2">2. That the Prince ſhall repair to their City at pleaſure, and be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived upon his entry with all re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect and reverence, as was uſed in times paſt to his predeceſſors, Lieu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenants of <hi>Holland,</hi> and have acceſs into their Aſſemblies.</p>
               <p n="3">3. That the Lords of <hi>Amſterdam</hi> ſhall at the next Aſſembly of the States, uſe their utmoſt endeavours to allay all jealouſies and to recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cile differences in reference to the late action, and bury all in oblivion.</p>
               <pb n="42" facs="tcp:170024:26"/>
               <p n="4">4. That the Lords <hi>Andrew</hi> and <hi>Cornelius Bicher,</hi> ſhall forthwith be removed from Government, with reſpect had to their good Names, Integrity and future Security; and if after they have had conference with his Highneſſe the <hi>Prince of Orange</hi> he ſhall perſiſt in his opinion touching them, that then they ſhall be rendred uncapable of any Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment hereafter.</p>
               <p>Now though by this means he brought the States under his Lure, and ſubjugated them to his hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour; yet this was not the prize he run for, his greateſt hopes and higheſt thoughts being fix'd on that inexhauſtible treaſure then in the bank at <hi>Amſterdam,</hi> with which he might not only have rais'd his declining ſtate, but alſo mount to an abſolute degree of So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraignty and Supremacy over that people, and likewiſe might have contributed much towards the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pairing
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:170024:26"/>the deſpicable and needy fortunes of his Brother in Law the <hi>Scots King,</hi> to the troubling and diſquieting the peace and tranquil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of theſe three Nations; to all which it pleaſed God of his good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe to give a check.</p>
               <p>The State of <hi>France</hi> had likewiſe a plentifull ſhare in thoſe incum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brances and common calamities that are incident to Nations and people by reaſon of forreign and domeſtique broyls; The preſent Cardinall <hi>Mazarine</hi> was lookt up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on as the very efficient cauſe of all their civill diſcords, and the only eye-ſoar of that miſerable people; not much unlike the late blazing Star of <hi>Canterbury</hi> in <hi>England,</hi> both Church men and yet both Stateſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, of like Intereſt with their King, and of like power over the people, both alike emulated by the Nobility for their Greatneſſe, and of the Commonalty for their grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vances;
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:170024:27"/>But like Fate hath not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fell them; For this Cardinall is neither out of favour with his Prince, nor is he fallen into the hands of the people, for though they have often ſhewed their teeth, it hath never been in their power to bite.</p>
               <p>For during the minority of the preſent King of <hi>France Lewis</hi> the 14. the ſole management of State-affairs hath been in the hands of the Queen <hi>Regent,</hi> and her beloved Favourite Cardinall <hi>Mazarine;</hi> at which (after ſome years forbear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance) the chief of the Nobility utter'd their diſcontents both privately and publikely: whereup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on three of them were arreſted and ſent to priſon, <hi>viz. Lewis de Bour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bon</hi> Prince of <hi>Conde, Armant de Bourbon</hi> Prince of <hi>Conti,</hi> and the Duke of <hi>Longueville;</hi> this admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtred freſh occaſion to the people to breathe out their diſcontents,
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:170024:27"/>thoſe of <hi>Burdeaux</hi> againſt the Duke of <hi>Eſpernon</hi> more eſpecially, but all againſt the Cardinall; So that on a ſudden the whole Kingdome was inflam'd with civil wars, and the appurtenances thereunto belong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. The principall promoters of and actors in thoſe tumults were two famous <hi>Amazones,</hi> the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe of <hi>Conde,</hi> and the Dutcheſſe of <hi>Longueville</hi> in behalf of their impriſon'd husbands; Many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers of quality appear'd alſo in their behalf, and to make them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves the more formidable, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracted an underhand bargain with the Spaniard, who (greedy to fiſh in ſuch troubled waters) ſupplied them with conſiderable ſummes of money: The Parliaments of <hi>Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deaux, Paris, Dijon, Tholouſe,</hi> &amp;c. countenanced theſe deſigns in op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition to the Cardinall and his creatures; So that in ſhort ſpace Armies were raiſed on both ſides,
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:170024:28"/>Towns garriſon'd, taken and re-ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, many mens lives loſt, and the Countrey prey'd upon by all par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties; The Spaniard being not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly a fomenter of, but an actor in theſe portentous diviſions, for by this means he had the opportunity to march to and fro in that Nation, without any conſiderable oppoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, taking Garriſons, and waſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Countrey at his plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure.</p>
               <p>Theſe Inſurrections (after many ebbing and flowings, ſtrange Revo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutions and tranſmigrations, too tedious here to inſert,) at length produc'd the liberty of the Princes, the withdrawing the Duke of <hi>Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pernon</hi> from <hi>Bourdeaux,</hi> the baniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Cardinall with all his kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred and friends from the Court and Kingdom: yet was he longer baniſhing then baniſhed; for it was not many moneths ere he return'd in great pomp and glory, to the
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:170024:28"/>extream grief of his old malecon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents and competitors, the Prince of <hi>Conde,</hi> the Duke of <hi>Orleance</hi> and others; as appears by the preſent troubles wherewith that ſervile people is yet afflicted: where (pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for their deliverance) I ſhall leave them, and return to the more proper ſubject of this diſcourſe, <hi>viz.</hi> the Engliſh affairs in <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The moneth of <hi>Auguſt</hi> was neer done, and little action perform'd ſave the taking of <hi>Collington</hi> houſe and <hi>Readhall</hi> by ſtorm, and in it the Laird <hi>Hamilton,</hi> Major <hi>Hamilton</hi> and 60 Souldiers, 60 Barrels of Pouder, 100 Arms, great ſtore of Meal, Malt, Beer, Wine and other rich plunder: This was done on the 24<hi rend="sup">th</hi> of <hi>Aug.</hi> 1650.</p>
               <p>The body of the Engliſh Army remov'd forthwith from <hi>Pencland</hi> Hills, to <hi>Collington, Readhall</hi> and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther parts within a mile of the
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:170024:29"/>whole Army of the <hi>Scots;</hi> on the 27<hi rend="sup">th</hi> both Armies march'd ſide by ſide, a great bog only betwixt them, which hindred an engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, yet the great Guns plaid on both ſides: <hi>Aug.</hi> 28<hi rend="sup">th</hi> the Canon from the Engliſh Camp plaid hard upon the Enemy and greatly an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noy'd them, all which provoked them not to fight, but ſtill they kept within the protection of the Bog: The Engliſh (being in ſome want of Proviſions) drew off to their old Quarters at <hi>Pencland</hi> Hills, then with much difficulty to <hi>Muſslebur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough</hi> to recruit, which done, they drew off their Forces, quitted their Garriſons, and marched to <hi>Had<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dington;</hi> the <hi>Scots</hi> attending on their right wing, fell into their Quarters with a reſolute Party, and were as valiantly repuls'd by a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giment of Foot commanded by Coll. <hi>Fairfax.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Septemb.</hi> 1. The <hi>Scots</hi> being ſo
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:170024:29"/>advantagiouſly drawn up at the weſt end of the Town, the Engliſh drew Eaſtward into fair and cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pion ground, fit for both Armies to engage in: but finding (after ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall hours expectation of the ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies approach) that they would not move after them, but to dog them to advantages, they marched towards <hi>Dunbar,</hi> whether the <hi>Scots</hi> mov'd apace after them, and at a Paſſe endeavoured to fall upon the rear, which the Engliſh perceiving fac'd about to fight them: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon the <hi>Scots</hi> drew off to the Hills, perceiving their advantage lay there, to impede the Engliſh at the Paſſe at <hi>Copperſpeth;</hi> which being effected, they brag'd they had the Engliſh in <hi>Eſſex</hi> his pound, mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing they had them upon the ſame lock the King had the Earl of <hi>Eſſex</hi> at in <hi>Cornwall:</hi> ſo ready are men to promiſe wonders to themſelves, while they confer but with their own deſires.</p>
               <pb n="50" facs="tcp:170024:30"/>
            </div>
            <div n="50-100" type="part">
               <p>The Engliſh were indeed invi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roned with all manner of apparent dangers; their Forces were leſſned, their bodies weakned with Fluxes, their ſtrength waſted with watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, in want of drink; wet and cold weather they were alwaies accompanied with, and much im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paired in point of courage, 2000 at leaſt being diſabled for preſent ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, were ſent at ſeverall times to <hi>Barwick.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Generall and his Councell of Officers finding the Army unfit for further delayes,<note place="margin">The <hi>Scots</hi> defeated at <hi>Dunbar.</hi>
                  </note> reſolved next morning to break through that their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſraelitiſh condition, by falling on the right wing of the <hi>Scots,</hi> and either force a paſſage that way, or periſh in the attempt; and being imbattail'd by break of day accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly, they fell upon the enemy with Horſe and Foot very unani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouſly; who to hinder the Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh at a Paſſe, drew up all their
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:170024:30"/>Horſe upon their right wing, and valiantly receiv'd the onſet: The Word of the Engliſh was <hi>The Lord of Hoſts;</hi> and that of the <hi>Scots</hi> was <hi>The Covenant:</hi> The Engliſh as men indued with new ſtrength from on high, vigorouſly preſt forward, as reſolved to become abſolute van<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſhers or to die Martyrs. After one hours ſharp diſpute, the <hi>Scots</hi> were wholly routed, their Cavilry fled, and the Infantry were all or moſt of them ſlain and taken to the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of about 15000. There were taken 200 Colours, 10 Collonels, 12 Lieutenant Collonels, 9 Majors, 47 Captains, 72 Lieutenants, 80 Enſignes beſides Cornets and Quartermaſters: 22 Pieces of Ord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, with ſeverall ſmaller Pieces, about 15000 Arms; thoſe of Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity taken, were the Lord <hi>Libber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton</hi> and his Sonne, the Lord <hi>Cran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſton,</hi> S<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>James Lumſdale</hi> Liutenant Gen. of the Foot, Adjutant Gen.
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:170024:31"/>
                  <hi>Bickerton,</hi> Scoutmaſter Generall <hi>Cambill,</hi> &amp;c. At this engagement all the Forces of the Engliſh would not amount to 1200, and the <hi>Scots</hi> were in number more then 20000. And as there was a generall Faſt throughout <hi>England,</hi> to implore a bleſſing from Heaven upon the proceedings of their Army in <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> ſo likewiſe there was ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed a ſolemne day of Thankſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giving to Almighty God, for this mighty Victory obtain'd over the <hi>Scots</hi> in the fields of <hi>Dunbar,</hi> Sept. 3. 1650. in the obſervation whereof many of the Clergy ſhew'd them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves very froward and obſtinate, of whom I ſhall have occaſion to ſpeak more hereafter.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Scot.</hi> 7<hi rend="sup">th</hi>. 4 Regiments of Foot marched into <hi>Lieth,</hi> where they found 37 Guns mounted on Plat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forms, ſome Shot and Ammuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion with ſtore of wealth.</p>
               <p>The ſame day the Lord Gen.
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:170024:31"/>
                  <hi>Cromwell</hi> drew the reſt of his Army both Horſe and Foot into <hi>Edenbur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough,</hi> without any loſſe ſave the Arm of a Souldier taken off by a Canon bullet from the Caſtle: <hi>Sept.</hi> 6<hi rend="sup">th</hi> being Sabbath day, Generall <hi>Cromwell</hi> ſent a Trumpeter into the Caſtle, to invite the Miniſters to come to their ſeverall Charges, which they refuſed, ſo that the Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh ſupplied their places.</p>
               <p>For ſome certain time the Army was buſied in compleating the For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifications at <hi>Lieth,</hi> the moſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modious Harbor for their accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modation in all <hi>Scotland.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Gen. <hi>Cromwell</hi> (after he had cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed a Protection for Markets, and Liberty of Trade in <hi>Edenburrough</hi> and <hi>Lieth</hi> to be proclaimed by beat of Drum and ſound of Trumpet) marched forward <hi>Sep.</hi> 14<hi rend="sup">th</hi> with his Army to <hi>Netheriſh,</hi> 6 miles from <hi>Edenburrough,</hi> leaving Maj. Gen. <hi>Overton</hi> with his Brigade behind.
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:170024:32"/>
                  <hi>Sep.</hi> 15<hi rend="sup">th</hi> the Army marched be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond <hi>Linlithgow,</hi> but (by reaſon of the extremity of the weather) they were forc't to quarter there that night. <hi>Sep.</hi> 16<hi rend="sup">th</hi> they marched to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards <hi>Falkirke;</hi> and from thence <hi>Sep.</hi> 17<hi rend="sup">th</hi> within a mile of <hi>Sterling. Sep.</hi> 18<hi rend="sup">th</hi> a Councell of Warre was called, and a Letter drawn up to be ſent into the Town, expreſſing their conſtant affection to, and ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſſe of the People of <hi>Scotland,</hi> which though they had not taken the deſired effect, yet being ſo far advanc'd into the Country with their Army, they now deſired them to take into conſideraiton their former Papers, and deliver up that place for the ſervice of the Commonwealth of <hi>England.</hi> A Trumpeter being ſent with the Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, a Gentleman on foot, with a Pike in his hand met him, and told him They would not let him come in, nor receive his Letter.</p>
               <pb n="55" facs="tcp:170024:32"/>
               <p>In the afternoon came a Trum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peter from the <hi>Scots,</hi> deſiring a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leaſe of Priſoners upon ran<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ome: To which Generall <hi>Cromwell</hi> an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered, That they came not thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to make merchandize of Men, or to get gain to themſelves, but for the ſervice and ſecurity of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealth of <hi>England.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The ſame day Orders were iſſued forth for the Horſe and Foot to march towards <hi>Sterling,</hi> in order to a ſtorm, Ladders and all other ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſaries being provided for that purpoſe; but the ſtrength of the enemy, and of the place, with other diſadvantages being conſidered, it was reſolved that the Army ſhould draw off; which accordingly they did <hi>Sep.</hi> 19. and marched to <hi>Lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lithgow,</hi> which when the Generall and his Officers had viewed, order was given for making ſeverall Works for the ſecurity of the place, conceiving it might make a very
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:170024:33"/>conſiderable frontier Garriſon, ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the heart of the Country, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween <hi>Edinburrough</hi> and <hi>Sterling:</hi> whence (leaving there 5 Troops of Horſe, and 6 Companies of Foot) Gen. <hi>Cromwell</hi> with the reſt of the Army marched back to <hi>Edenbur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough. Sept.</hi> 23. The Gen. and Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers kept a day of Humiliation.</p>
               <p>About the ſame time the Kirk party alſo appointed a ſolemne Faſt,</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. To humble themſelves for their too much confidence in the arm of fleſh.</item>
                  <item>2. For the malignity and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phaneneſſe of their Army.</item>
                  <item>3. For the Plunderings and wickedneſſe of their Army when they were in <hi>England.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>4. For their not ſufficient purg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their Army.</item>
                  <item>5. For their Commiſſioners un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawfull and ſurreptitious manner of proſecuting the Treaty with their
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:170024:33"/>King, and their crooked wayes in bringing him home.</item>
                  <item>6. For their not ſufficient purg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Kings houſe.</item>
                  <item>7. For the juſt grounds they have, that his Majeſties Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance was not found, nor from the heart.</item>
               </list>
               <p>From which time to the moneths end, little was done, ſave that Gen. <hi>Cromwell</hi> took order for the effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuall reducing of the Caſtle of <hi>Edinburrough:</hi> for which purpoſe many miners both Scotch and Engliſh were procur'd to expedite the buſineſſe. <hi>Sep.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>0. The Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh went ſo neer the works of the Caſtle, as they carried away one of the Scots Colours, 300 Muskets with other Arms, without any loſſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Octob.</hi> 1. The Scots Galleries went on in order to ſpringing the Mines, they ſent many great and ſmall ſhot among them, yet nothing
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:170024:34"/>retarded the work. <hi>Octob.</hi> 2. the Engliſh made a ſearch in the high Church at <hi>Edenburgh,</hi> and found there one great Iron Gun, 200 new Muskets, 16 barrels of Pouder, 6<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> bundles of Bandileers, 200 Swords, 200 new Halberts, 300 new Pikes, and two load of Match. That which was done the remain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing part of this moneth, was chief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to beget a right underſtanding and compliance with thoſe that diſſented from the King and Kirk, <hi>viz.</hi> Col. <hi>Kerre</hi> and <hi>Straughan</hi> and their adherents: for which purpoſe Gen <hi>Cromwell</hi> ſent Commiſ. Gen. <hi>Whaley</hi> with his own and another Regiment towards them: in the mean while the Fortifications at <hi>Lieth,</hi> and the mining at <hi>Eden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burgh</hi> went on proſperouſly: Then Gen. <hi>Cromwell</hi> with the reſidue of the Army marched towards <hi>Glaſco,</hi> but finding there little encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment for longer ſtay, they quickly
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:170024:34"/>returned, and in their way Garri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonned two ſtrong Houſes, both to enlarge their Quarters, and to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent the Moſſe-Troopers from ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curing themſelves there.</p>
               <p>Let the Reader now judge what a diſaſterous condition this Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple was in, that when an enemy was in the very heart of the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, there ſhould be ſo many di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtractions and civill diſcords a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong themſelves, even to the kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling and ſlaying one another: One Party in the North was for the King without the Kirk; another Party in the Weſt was for the Kirk without the King; a third was for King and Kirk; and theſe were they then at <hi>Sterling</hi> that bore the greateſt ſway; <hi>viz.</hi> The Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittee of Eſtates and Generall Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembly; all theſe had their Swords drawn one againſt the other. When things were at this paſſe, Gen. <hi>Cromwell</hi> ſent a Letter to the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittee
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:170024:35"/>of Eſtates, and another of the ſame to Col. <hi>Kerre</hi> and <hi>Straug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>han,</hi> much like the former, and produc'd like effect. Commiſ. Gen. <hi>Whaley</hi> that was ſent with a party towards <hi>Kerre</hi> and <hi>Straughan,</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coſted them firſt with a Letter, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claring, <hi>That it was not unknown what Amicable wayes they had us'd, to avoid the effuſion of Christian bloud, before and ſince they came into</hi> Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, <hi>which though hitherto had been ineffectual, yet they ſhould endeavour the ſame;</hi> Shewing further, <hi>that their Arms were ſtill stretcht out rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to embrace them, whenever God ſhould incline them to come in, and that they ſought not domination over them, to enſlave them, nor to depreſſe their Kirk-Government, neither that they ſought their Goods or Eſtates, but to carry on the Lords work: And that if they would ſtill be blinded, and perſiſt in gainſaying and oppoſing, then what further miſery befell their Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:170024:35"/>by Famine or Sword, would lie heavy on them.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This Letter (though ſavouring ſo much of integrity and ingenuity) met with nothing of like nature from their Adverſaries, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding their pretended deſire of hearkning to an accommodation.</p>
               <p>For within ſhort ſpace after Col. <hi>Kerre</hi> ſent a Letter to Commiſſary Gen. <hi>Whaley</hi> then at <hi>Carliſle,</hi> which being contracted ſpeaks after this ſort; That though they were not in a capacity againſt the unjuſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaſion of the Engliſh, yet were they in a capacity to ſuffer, and ſhould ſubmit to Gods will, either by do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing or ſuffering, until the time of their deliverance come; and that if it were their happineſſe to periſh in their duty, it would be a ſufficient mercy to them: and when the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution had arrived to its height, their captivity ſhould be return'd, adding that he thought it ſtrange
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:170024:36"/>the Engliſh ſhould talk of a ceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, even while they were capti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vating their poor people, aſſaulting their Gariſons, apprehending their godly Miniſters, tearing them from their holy callings, and from their holy ſighing flocks: concluding, that the departure of the Engliſh out of that Kingdom, and then de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiring a Chriſtian Treaty or confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence with them, would be a fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour and mercy equally as great to the one as the other. Theſe were the effects of that (I will not ſay miſguided) zeal, by which theſe men were acted.</p>
               <p>About the latter end of this Moneth,<note place="margin">Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> dies.</note> the <hi>Prince of Orange</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted this life, who ſo lately had put a hook into the Noſtrils, and a Bridle into the mouths of the high and mighty States, and in him the <hi>Scots</hi> King loſt the great intereſt he had in thoſe parts; whom, though the States for his
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:170024:36"/>late Actions when he was living hated, yet when dead they lament<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed: About ten daies after this,<note place="margin">The Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered of a Son.</note> the <hi>Princeſs of Orange</hi> was delivered of a Son, which did in part mitigate the grief that was conceiv'd for the death of the Prince.</p>
               <p>Now ſeeing the <hi>Scots</hi> ſtill ſlight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed all the wayes and means of a lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving and friendly compliance, as appear'd by another Letter from Coll. <hi>Kerre</hi> to Commiſſ. Gen. <hi>Wha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ley,</hi> wherein he adviſes them to ſtand upon his Guard, and expect no further Overtures; the Engliſh ſet upon new undertakings, and by a party of Horſe under Maj. <hi>Brown</hi> took in a ſtrong place called <hi>Dal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſe,</hi> and in it 50 Muskets, 50 Pikes, 4 Barrels of Pouder, ſome ſtore of Proviſions and Provender: this was a ſuppoſed Harbor for thoſe villa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous people the Moſſe-Troopers, who murthered divers Engliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men ſtragling or going for Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions;
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:170024:37"/>they likewiſe ſurpriſed a party of Moſſe-Troopers in <hi>Dar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lington</hi> Caſtle, ſome of which were ſhot preſently upon the place. Then advanc'd Coll. <hi>Monke</hi> with a party of Horſe and Foot to reduce <hi>Roſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lane</hi> Caſtle 7 miles from <hi>Edinbur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough,</hi> which (when he had ſent in ſome Granadoes among them) was yeelded upon mercy: Maj. Gen. <hi>Lambert</hi> preſently after with a party of 2000 Horſe marched towards <hi>Dumfreez,</hi> Coll. <hi>Kerre</hi> being then about <hi>Peebles;</hi> Commiſ. Gen <hi>Wha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ley</hi> in his march towards the ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, took in <hi>Dalketh</hi> Caſtle with a threatning Summons, where was ſtore of Arms, Ordnance, Pouder, Match and Bullet; the wall of it was 13 foot broad at the top: Now Coll. <hi>Lambert</hi> having (not without ſome difficulty) got over <hi>Hambleton</hi> River, quartered there that night; Coll. <hi>Kerre</hi> having notice thereof early next morning, reſolved to
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:170024:37"/>beat up their Quarters and fall in upon them,<note place="margin">Col. <hi>Kers</hi> patty de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feated, and himſelf taken pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoner.</note> and ſo to ſurpriſe the Maj. Generall, all which he at tempted with courage; but the Engliſh having a timely Alarme, on a ſudden encompaſſed moſt of the enemies Horſe, of whom they killed 100 and took 100, they took likewiſe 400 Horſe and Furniture, forſook of the Riders, and purſued the reſt as farre as <hi>Ayre;</hi> in which purſuit Col. <hi>Kerre</hi> himſelf was wounded and taken,<note place="margin">Colonell <hi>Straughan</hi> came in to Major Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral <hi>Lam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bert.</hi>
                  </note> with his Capt. Lieut. Lieutenant Colonell, and <hi>Straughans</hi> Major, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Colonell <hi>Straughan,</hi> Capt. <hi>Giffin</hi> with ſome others of the diſſenters in the Weſt, came then in to the Major Generall, who brought them all forthwith to the Head-Quarters at <hi>Edenburgh.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>December;</hi> The Engliſh having raiſed a battery, planted their morter-peece and great Canon a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>Edenburgh</hi> Caſtle, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gun
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:170024:38"/>to play; the Enemy hung out a Flag of defiance in contempt thereof: but they had not plaid long ere they took it in, whereby it was conceived ſome notable ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecution was done by four or five ſhels that fell among them, and forthwith put out a white Flag on the top of the Caſtle, and ſent forth a Drummer offering to ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>render if they might have leave to ſend to the Committee of Eſtates: which being denied they accepted of a Treaty, and ſent Major <hi>Aber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nethy</hi> and Capt. <hi>Hinderſon</hi> to treat on their part: Col. <hi>Monk</hi> and Lieut. Col <hi>White</hi> were appointed to treat in behalf of the Engliſh, the reſult whereof was to this effect.</p>
               <p>That the Caſtle of <hi>Edenburgh</hi> ſhould be ſurrendred up to his Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency the Lord General <hi>Cromwel</hi> on the 24. of <hi>Decemb.</hi> 1650. with all the Ordinance,<note place="margin">The ſtrong and impregna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Caſtle of <hi>Eden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burgh</hi> ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rendred to the Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh.</note> Arms, Maga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zine, and Furniture of War there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto belonging.</p>
               <pb n="67" facs="tcp:170024:38"/>
               <p>That the Governour with all the Officers and Souldiers, ſhould then march forth with their Arms, Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lours flying, Drums beating; mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches lighted and Bullet in mouth to ſuch place, as they ſhall chooſe.</p>
               <p>That ſuch Inhabitants adjacent as have any goods in the Caſtle, ſhall have them reſtored unto them; and to that purpoſe they had liberty from the 19. to the 24. of <hi>Decemb.</hi> to fetch them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way. There was taken in this ſtrong-hold 5 French Canon, 5 Dutch half Canon, 2 Culverings, 2 Demi-culverings, 2 Minion, 2 Faulcon, 28 Braſte Drakes, 2 Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tards, about 7000 Arms, 80 Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rels of Powder, ſtore of Canon Shot, with other proviſions pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portionable.</p>
               <p>It may ſeem ſtrange and almoſt incredible, that ſuch a ſtrong and impregnable hold as was that, ſhould be ſo eaſily won, the like
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:170024:39"/>whereof is not in that Nation; wherefore it was the common vogue of that time, and by many credibly beleeved, That it was aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaulted with ſilver engines; But whether it was covetouſneſſe, co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardiſe, Treachery or want that cauſed this ſudden rendition, I know not: But this I know and am ſure, it made as much for, and was of as great importance to the Engliſh, as can be imagined: for while that buſineſſe was yet in ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence, the Army was hindred from many attempts of great con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence.</p>
               <p>Nor was the Parliament of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> leſſe fortunate in their mari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time affairs: for the Engliſh Fleet under the command of Gen. <hi>Blake</hi> lying before <hi>Lizbon,</hi> after they had deſtroyed ſeverall French Pirates, taken many Sugar Prizes belong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the King of <hi>Portugal,</hi> of great value, and ſcowr'd the Seas
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:170024:39"/>in ſome ſort of ſuch others as had been ſo extreamly prejudiciall to the Engliſh Merchants, eſpecially thoſe trading into the Levant Seas; They were conſtrain'd part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly by diſtreſſe of weather, and partly to revictuall and water, to make for ſome other port: in which time Prince <hi>Rupert</hi> with his Fleet (making a vertue of neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity) hoiſted ſail, and ſteerd their courſe for <hi>Malaga,</hi> where they burnt and ſpoil'd ſeverall Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants Ships: Gen. <hi>Blake</hi> hereup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on reduc'd his Fleet to 7 ſtout and nimble Frigots, and ſent the reſt home with the Prizes, and with them he made all the Sail he could after the Enemy, and coming to <hi>Malaga</hi> heard they were gone to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards <hi>Alicant,</hi> Gen. <hi>Blake</hi> ſailing thence betwixt <hi>Cape degat</hi> and <hi>Cape de Paulo</hi> took a French Ship of 20 Guns, and preſently after that the Roe-buck one of the revolted
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:170024:40"/>Ships fell into their hands, after which they met with the Black Prince another of <hi>Ruperts</hi> Fleet, which to avoid being taken, ran aſhoar and blew her ſelf up: next day 4 more of <hi>Ruperts</hi> Fleet ran a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhoar in the Bay of <hi>Cartagena,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Prince <hi>Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perts</hi> Fleet deſtroy'd.</note> where they were caſt away and bulged: Some few daies after Generall <hi>Blake</hi> ſet ſail to ſeek out the reſt of <hi>Ruperts</hi> Fleet, which were two, ſteering his courſe to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards <hi>Minorca, Majorca, Humaterra;</hi> but miſſing of them he gave over the Chaſe, and returned for <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> having done as much as could be expected from men valiant and faithfull, to the great encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Merchants, content<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the people, and joy of all well-affected people.</p>
               <p>Notwithſtanding all this, ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall deſigns were ſet on foot by un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiet and wayward ſpirits in behalf of <hi>Charles Stuart,</hi> ſome by open
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:170024:40"/>inſurrection, others by ſecret com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bination, in which the Clergy had no ſmall ſhare, as ſhall be declared hereafter.</p>
               <p>There was executed at <hi>Tiburne</hi> one <hi>Benſon</hi> for acting by vertue of a Commiſſion from the <hi>Scots</hi> King,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Benſon</hi> an Agent from the Scots King exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted at <hi>Tiburn.</hi>
                  </note> being in the ſame conſpiracy with Col. <hi>Andrews</hi> who was beheaded as aforeſaid.</p>
               <p>Upon the ſame account roſe a mutinous rabble in the County of <hi>Norfolk,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">An Inſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection in <hi>Norfolk.</hi>
                  </note> who for a while went ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving to and again, pretending the ends of that undertaking, was for the aboliſhing of Popery, reſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the young King to his Crown, revenge of his Fathers death, for ſuppreſſion of hereſie and ſchiſm; But as it was begun without order, ſo was it manag'd without reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: For the Parliament were no time-givers to growing dangers, but immediatly gave order for the ſuppreſſing them; So that 200
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:170024:41"/>Horſe from <hi>Lyn</hi> and 3 Troops of Horſe from the Army, with ſome of the <hi>Militia</hi> Forces of that County,<note place="margin">is appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed and the ring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leaders executed.</note> marched towards them, upon which they were preſently diſperſed, and ſome taken, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of about 20 were executed, who becauſe they were perſons of no great eminency, I ſhall forbear troubling the Reader with their Names.</p>
               <p>About this time alſo Sir <hi>Henry Hide</hi> being commiſſionated as Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſadour from the <hi>Scots</hi> King to the Grand <hi>Signior</hi> at <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Sir <hi>Henry Hide</hi> exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted at the Old Exchange</note> ſtood in competition with Sir <hi>Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas Bendiſh</hi> (then Embaſſadour for the Engliſh) for his place: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon they had a hearing before the Vizier <hi>Baſſa,</hi> the reſult whereof was, that Sir <hi>Thomas Bendiſh</hi> ſhould diſpoſe of the ſaid Sir <hi>Henry Hide,</hi> as he thought good, who was ſtraightway ſent to <hi>Smyrna,</hi> thence into <hi>England,</hi> and there condemn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:170024:41"/>and executed for a traitor before the Royal Exchange in <hi>London.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The warre in <hi>Scotland</hi> was now almoſt at a ſtand, for the ſharpneſs of the Winter was ſuch in that Northern Climate, that much could not be expected, yet were all probable deſigns for the reducing that obſtinate and hardy people put in execution.<note place="margin">The Scots King crowned at <hi>Scone. Jan.</hi> 30. 1651.</note> The <hi>Scots</hi> were chiefly buſied about the Corona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of their King, which was per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed at <hi>Scone,</hi> Jan. 1. 1651. with as much ſolemnity and gallantry as their neceſſity and poverty would permit; then they proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to the Excommunication of <hi>Straughan, Swinton,</hi> and others that came in to the Engliſh, made a ſhift to unite the other Diſſenting parties, and then put out an Act for new Levies to be made throughout the Nation.</p>
               <p>Soon after this Lieut. Gen. <hi>David Leſley</hi> with a party of 800 Horſe
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:170024:42"/>made an attempt upon <hi>Lithgow</hi> where was a Regiment of Horſe under Col. <hi>Sanderſon,</hi> who being preſently in a readineſſe to receive them, the <hi>Scots</hi> retreated without entring the Town.</p>
               <p>Next attempt of the Engliſh was for reducing of <hi>Hume</hi> Caſtle with two Regiments of Horſe and Foot commanded by Col. <hi>Fenwick,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Hume</hi> Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieg'd,</note> who coming before it, ſent in this Sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, which with the anſwer for the unuſuall ſtrain thereof, I here inſert.</p>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <opener>
                        <salute>Sir,</salute>
                     </opener>
                     <p>HIs Excellency the Lord Generall <hi>Cromwell</hi> hath commanded me to reduce this Caſtle you now poſſeſſe, under his obedience, which if you now deliver into my hands, for his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, you ſhall have fit terms for your ſelf and thoſe with you, and eaſe the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jacent parts of a great charge; If you refuſe, I doubt not but in a ſhort time,
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:170024:42"/>by the Lords aſsiſtance to obtain what now I demand. I expect your anſwer by <hi>7.</hi> of the Clock tomorrow morning, and reſt,</p>
                     <trailer>
                        <hi>To the Governour of</hi> Hume <hi>Caſtle.</hi>
                     </trailer>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>Your Servant, <hi>George Fenwick.</hi>
                        </signed>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <opener>
                        <salute>Right Honourable,</salute>
                     </opener>
                     <p>
                        <hi>I</hi> Have received a Trumpeter of yours, as he tels me, without the Paſſe, to render <hi>Hume</hi> Caſtle to the Lord Generall <hi>Cromwell:</hi> Pleaſe you, I never ſaw your General, nor knew your Generall, as for <hi>Hume</hi> Caſtle it ſtands upon a rock: Given at <hi>Hume</hi> Caſtle this day before <hi>7</hi> a clock, ſo reſteth without prejudice to my Native Countrey.</p>
                     <trailer>For the Governour of <hi>Barwick,</hi>
                     </trailer>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>Your most humble Servant,<note place="margin">aſſaulted and taken.</note> 
                           <hi>Th. Cockburne.</hi>
                        </signed>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <p>Notwithſtanding this reſolute and conceited anſwer, when the Engliſh with their Culverin and
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:170024:43"/>morter-piece had opened a ſmall breach, the Enemy beat a parley, and becauſe they might not have ſuch conditions as they would, they were forc't to take ſuch as they could get, <hi>viz.</hi> to ſurender upon mercy, which was done ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly.</p>
               <p>Then Col. <hi>Monk</hi> with about 3 Regiments of Horſe and Foot, laid Siege to <hi>Tymptallon</hi> Caſtle, againſt which they plaid with their mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar-pieces for the ſpace of 48 hours, but did them no hurt; then they plaid at the Caſtle with 6 battering Guns,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Timptallon</hi> Caſtle taken.</note> which did ſuch notable ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecution, that the Enemy beat a parley, and deſired terms to march away, but none would be granted, ſave that they ſhould yeeld them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to mercy, which was at laſt accepted, and the Caſtle yeelded, with all the Guns, Arms, Ammu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nition, and proviſion therein: The taking of this Caſtle was of great
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:170024:43"/>concernment to the Engliſh, who were ever and anon taken and rifled by the Garriſon; So that now the paſſage from <hi>Edenburgh</hi> to <hi>Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wick,</hi> was in a manner cleer. Not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding which and all the care that had been uſed, the Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh were daily ſurpriz'd and mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered in ſmall ſtragling parties; in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomuch that Gen. <hi>Cromwell</hi> was forc't (for the ſafeguard of his men) to publiſh and ſtrictly to put in execution the following Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clamation.</p>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <p>FInding that divers under my com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand are not only daily ſpoiled and robbed, but alſo ſometimes barbarouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and inhumanely ſlain by a ſort of out-laws and robbers, not under the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipline of any Army, and finding that all our tenderneſſe to the Countrey, produceth no better effect, then their compliance with and protection of ſuch perſons, and conſidering that it
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:170024:44"/>is in the power of the Countrey to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tect and diſcover them, many of them being inhabitants of thoſe places where commonly the out-rage is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted, and perceiving that their mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is ordinarily by the invitation, and according to intelligence given them by Countreymen; I do therefore declare, that whereſoever any under my command, ſhall be hereafter robbed or ſpoiled by ſuch parties, I will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire life for life, and a plenary ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction for their Goods, of thoſe Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhes and places where the fact ſhall be committed, unleſſe they ſhall diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver and produce the offender; and this I wiſh all perſons to take notice of, that none may pleade ignorance. Gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven under my hand at <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> Novemb. <hi>5. 1650.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>O. Cromwell.</signed>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <p>Hereupon ſeverall Sums of Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney were levied upon ſuch Pariſhes and places where any Robberies
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:170024:44"/>or Murthers were committed; and likewiſe ſuch perſons as were found to abett, act, or aſſiſt in the perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trating any murthers were forth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with condemned and executed, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the tenour of the afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid Proclamation.</p>
               <p>The Engliſh in the next place deſign'd the reducing of <hi>Brunt I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſland,</hi> and in order thereto they ſhip'd ſome of their Infantry; but either through the ignorance, mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtake, or neglect of the chief Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mander, the deſign for that time was fruſtrated.</p>
               <p>Gen. <hi>Cromwell</hi> with his Army marched from <hi>Edenburgh,</hi> and aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſay'd ſeverall times to paſſe over into <hi>Fife;</hi> but the violent ſeaſon and difficult paſſage, forc't them to betake themſelves to their for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Quarters, which were the more comfortable by reaſon of the Fleet of Ships that arriv'd at <hi>Lieth</hi> with plenty of proviſions for
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:170024:45"/>Horſe and Man; one whereof bound from <hi>Hamburgh</hi> with cheeſe, by diſtreſſe of weather was driven into the North of <hi>Scotland</hi> where it was ſeized: but the Maſter pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended he was bound for <hi>Haver de Grace</hi> in <hi>France,</hi> and producing old Cockets, importing as much, he was diſmiſt and a Scotch-man put himſelf and goods aboard for <hi>France;</hi> whereupon they ſet ſail, and about the <hi>Frith</hi> were boarded by an Iriſh Man of Warre, who would have carried the Veſſell to <hi>Ireland,</hi> alledging they were bound for <hi>Lieth,</hi> the Maſter ſtood to his former relation, and deſired they would take the report of a Scotch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man who was aboard; ſo that forthwith they left her, and ſhe came ſafe into <hi>Leith,</hi> whence the Scotchman was ſent home to car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry the News. Theſe with many other the ſupplies that were ſent from <hi>England</hi> were a great heart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:170024:45"/>to the Souldiers in the midſt of thoſe many hardſhips they were expos'd to by diſeaſes, and other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe; of which the General him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf had as great a ſhare as any, for he had ſo many violent fits of the contagious diſeaſe of that Countrey that brought him even to the brink of death; yet the weakneſſe and want of the Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall did neither abate the Souldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers courage, nor retard the enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſes they deſign'd for compleat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their work; although other difficulties preſented themſelves as ſo many mountains of oppoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, <hi>viz.</hi> the number of their ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies diſperſed all along the other ſide of the river to prevent their Landing, the danger of the paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage it ſelf, and the unſeaſonable<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the weather; theſe impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diments with the weak condition of the Engliſh, hindred any further proceedings for ſome ſpace of time.</p>
               <pb n="82" facs="tcp:170024:46"/>
               <p>During which Intervall there hapned as remarkable an accident in <hi>England</hi> as any Story can paral<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lel, which for the ſtrangeneſſe and rarity thereof may well merit my pains to recite, and the Readers patience to peruſe: At <hi>Oxford</hi> (the famous and renowned Nur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery of humane Literature) was tried, condemned, and executed, <hi>Anne Green,</hi> a Servant to Sir <hi>Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas Read</hi> at <hi>Ounſtu</hi> in that ſhire, who being with childe by a Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman in that Houſe (as ſhe affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to the laſt) about the fourth moneth of her time; over-work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing her ſelf fell in travell, and (not knowing what it might be) went to the Houſe of Office, where with ſome ſtraining the Childe fell from her unaware (as ſhe ſaid) being not above a ſpan long; and ſomething appearing in her Linnen that cauſed ſuſpicion, ſearch was made, and an abortive Infant found
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:170024:46"/>on the top of the Houſe of Office, ſo that 3 daies after (being in that time before ſome Juſtices of the Peace) ſhe was carried Priſoner to <hi>Oxford,</hi> where ſhe was condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and hang'd in the Caſtle-yard: After ſhe had hung about half an hour (during which time ſhe was puld by the Legs,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Anne Green</hi> hang'd at <hi>Oxford,</hi> af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terward ſhe reviv'd and is yet alive.</note> and ſtrook on the Breaſt by divers of her friends, and others, that ſhe might be out of her pain) ſhe was cut down, put into a Coffin, and brought to a Houſe to be diſſected before ſome Phyſicians: When they opened the Coffin, they perceived a rat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling in her throat, a Fellow ſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing by ſtamped upon her breaſt and belly; yet Doctor <hi>Petty</hi> and two or three more then preſent fell ſpeedily to uſe ſome means to bring her to life, and opened a vein, laid her in a warm bed, procur'd a woman to go into bed to her, and continued the uſe of divers other
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:170024:47"/>remedies, having reſpect to her ſenceleſneſſe, head, throat, and breaſt, ſo that in a few hours ſhe ſpake, the next day talked and coughed very heartily, and in ſhort ſpace perfectly recovered: Upon which firſt her reprieve, and then her pardon was procur'd: After this, ſhe (as upon the Gallows) ſtill inſiſted upon her innocency and integrity, in relation to the fact for which ſhe was condemn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. And indeed this was look'd upon as a ſpeciall providence of God thus to deliver her, who in the judgements of thoſe that un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood the buſineſſe was deemed guiltleſſe. Herein did the hand of God wonderfully appear, in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tecting the unadviſed actings of men, and in ſhewing us the dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger we are in, when we are ſway'd either by paſſion or prejudice a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the meaneſt of his Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures.</p>
               <pb n="85" facs="tcp:170024:47"/>
               <p>The Parliament weighing how prone the people were to adore the ſhadow of the late King, though the ſubſtance was deſtroy'd, cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed his Statue that was ſet up at the Weſt end of the Cathedrall of S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
                  <hi>Paul</hi> to be pulled down, and that alſo in the Royall Exchange, over which they cauſed to be wrote this Motto.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Exit Tyrannus Regum Ultimus Anno Libertatis Angliae restitutae Primo,</hi> Anno Domini 1648. <hi>Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuary</hi> 30.</p>
               <p>They likewiſe caus'd that badge of Monarchy the Kings Arms, to be defaced and expung'd out of all Churches, Chappels, and places of publike worſhip and Courts of Judicature throughout their Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minions, and this indeed was a means to make the giddy people forget the Garlick and Onyons of <hi>Egypt</hi> they much hankerd after.</p>
               <p>And to adde a more ſplendid lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtre
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:170024:48"/>to their ſtrength and great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe; they were highly courted by Embaſſadours from the Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bouring Nations, <hi>viz. Holland, Spain,</hi> and <hi>Portugall,</hi> yet the crafty <hi>Hollander</hi> held at a diſtance, as ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther willing the proſperity of the Royall party, then heartily deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, or effectually endeavouring a peace with them. The Spaniard as he had better ends, ſo had he better ſucceſſe; though in all his addreſſes he was ſtill re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minded of his ſuſpending and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laying the execution of juſtice up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Aſſaſſinates of the Engliſh Reſident at <hi>Madrid,</hi> ſince which time till now the controverſie be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the King and Church about that buſineſſe hath been in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Portugall</hi> Embaſſadour (af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter audience had before a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittee of Parliament,<note place="margin">The Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tugal Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſadour diſmiſt home.</note> and ſeveral applications unto them) not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:170024:48"/>fully impowerd, to give a ple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary ſatisfaction to the ſtate for their vaſt expences, and to the Merchants for their great loſſes, all occaſioned by them, was at length diſmiſt.</p>
               <p>Embaſſadours extraordinary were ſent from the Parliament of <hi>England</hi> to the States of the Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Provinces; their Names were <hi>Oliver</hi> S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
                  <hi>John,</hi> and <hi>Walter Strick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Engliſh Ambaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dors are ſent into <hi>Holland.</hi>
                  </note> men of ſingular parts and of approved integrity, who in gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lant equipage, with a magnificent train of followers, ſet ſail from the Downs, <hi>March</hi> 11. 1651. On the 12<hi rend="sup">th</hi> towards Evening, they came to anchor before <hi>Hellevoit ſlugs,</hi> but not without ſome danger: On the 13 they went in Boats to <hi>Roterdam,</hi> being met with veſſels from the States, then by the Engliſh Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants were conducted to the Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh houſe, and nobly entertain'd: During their ſtay there, the Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:170024:49"/>Embaſſador ſent a Gentleman to congratulate their ſaſe Arrivall, and to deſire there might be a fair correſpondency and right under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding between their Lordſhips and him. About two or three daies after they ſet forward for the <hi>Hague,</hi> where by the way the Maſter of the Ceremonies, with about 30 Coaches, met them, and entertain'd them with ſome Complements, and conducted them to a Houſe at the <hi>Hague,</hi> prepar'd for their rece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ption, where they were feaſted three daies by the States, and then had audience: where the Lord S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
                  <hi>John</hi> made a Learned and Elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent Speech in the Engliſh tongue and then delivered a Copy thereof in Dutch and Engliſh,<note place="margin">they have audience.</note> the heads whereof were in effect as fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows.</p>
               <p>That they were ſent over to the High and Mighty States of the Netherlands, from the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:170024:49"/>of the Common-wealth of <hi>England,</hi> to make a firm League and Confederacy between the two Republiques, if they think fit to accept thereof, notwithſtanding the many injuries the Engliſh have ſuſtain'd from the Dutch Nation.</p>
               <p>Secondly, To renew and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm thoſe former Treaties and A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greements of Trade and commerce made between the two Nations.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, He ſhewed them the notable advantages of <hi>England,</hi> in reſpect of the pleaſant and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modious ſcituation thereof, for the advancement of trade and all other accommodations.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, He told them he was commanded by the Parliament of the Common-wealth of <hi>England</hi> to let their Lordſhips know how highly they reſented the execrable murther of D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Doriſlaus</hi> their A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent, and that he doubted not but that their Lordſhips would uſe
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:170024:50"/>their utmoſt care and induſtry in cauſing a ſtrict and diligent ſearch to be made after the Authours thereof.</p>
               <p>After which the States (being acquainted with the many affronts the Ambaſſadors Gentlemen and others their attendants, had receiv'd from Engliſh Cavaliers and other ruffians) drew up a Proclamation and ſent it to the Ambaſſadours by the Lord <hi>Catz,</hi> to know whether they judged it full enough; the contents whereof was, To forbid all manner of perſons whatſoever, from giving any affront, either in word or deed, to any of the Ambaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſadours retinue, upon pain of corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall puniſhment.</p>
               <p>Three moneths was now ſpent in this tedious and coſtly Embaſſie, and nothing obtain'd ſave affronts and abuſes of all kindes, and the Sword of Juſtice not drawn in their behalf, againſt any one of that rio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:170024:50"/>rabble, that ſo frequently ſwarm'd at the Ambaſſadours gates, aſſaulting their ſervants, and reviling their perſons: of which injuries the Parliament being deep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſenſible, and wearied with ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectation of what fruits this Treaty would produce, Reſolved (That ſeeing all their Propoſals and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours for a laſting and well grounded Peace, were anſwered with dilatory ſhifts and evaſions, on purpoſe to gain time upon the Engliſh, till they ſaw on which ſide the chance of war in <hi>Scotland</hi> would fall) to call home their Ambaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dours; which ſudden and unex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected news did ſo ſurpriſe the Hoghen Mogens, that they courted them with frequent and unuſuall viſits; and with a multitude of feigned expreſſions,<note place="margin">they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn into <hi>England.</hi>
                  </note> laboured to beget a good opinion in the Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh of the reality of their intentions towards an amicable compliance
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:170024:51"/>with this Nation: notwithſtanding all which the Ambaſſadours ſoon after return into <hi>England infecta pace.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That which gave further cauſe of jealouſie to the Engliſh, that the Dutch plaid an underhand game with them was, becauſe Admirall <hi>Van-Trumpe</hi> with a Fleet of Ships lay hovering upon the Coaſts of <hi>Scilly,</hi> as though he would make an hoſtile attempt upon that place; but it being demanded of the States of <hi>Holland,</hi> what was the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigne of their Fleet in riding ſo neer that Iſland? it was anſwered, That they had no other deſigne therein, but to demand reſtitution of ſuch Ships and Goods as the Pyrates thereof had taken from their Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple: with which anſwer the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament were ſomewhat ſatisfied; but not to truſt them too far, ſpeedy order was taken for reducing the ſame into their own hands.</p>
               <pb n="93" facs="tcp:170024:51"/>
               <p>Accordingly on the 18<hi rend="sup">th</hi> of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pril</hi> 1651. Gen. <hi>Blake</hi> (with the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of a ſquadron of Ships com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded by S<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>George Aiſcue,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlands of <hi>Scilly</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duc'd.</note> that were deſigned for reducing of the <hi>Carybe</hi> Iſlands,) ſet ſail and landed 300 Seamen beſides Landmen up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Iſle: The Seamen with much reſolution, courage and gallantry, led the van, and eaſily made way for the reſt; ſo that they ſoon be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came maſters of the Iſlands of <hi>Treſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>co</hi> and <hi>Briers,</hi> took therein 150 Priſoners, and ſlew abut 20; they took alſo two conſiderable Frigots, the one of 18, the other of 32 Guns; they likewiſe became Maſters of the beſt Harbour belonging to thoſe Iſlands: hence the enemy fled to S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
                  <hi>Maries,</hi> their chief place of ſtrength, which in ſhort time was ſurrendred. As to the exceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing great ſtrength and commodious ſcituation of theſe Iſlands, I need not ſay much, for who ſo knowes
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:170024:52"/>thoſe parts, or hath obſerv'd the Card, will ſee what a neceſſity there was of reducing the ſame, and what a ſeaſonable mercy God was pleaſed to Crown their endeavours withall, that they ſhould gain ſo conſiderable a place as that, being fortified both by Nature and Art, without the loſſe of ten men from firſt to laſt.</p>
               <p>Upon miſ-information of the State of <hi>Cornet</hi> Caſtle in the Iſle of <hi>Guernſey,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Cornet Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle</hi> in <hi>Guernſey</hi> aſſaulted, but in vain.</note> that then held out for the Royall party, a conſiderable num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of Foot, with Ladders and all things neceſſary, gave an onſet; but whereas it was reported and beleeved that there was but 40 men in the Caſtle, and 18 of them unable for ſervice, it appeared af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tewards that there was 60 able men therein, enough to keep it againſt a far greater number, then was before it, ſo that their Ladders were beaten down and broken
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:170024:52"/>with ſtones, timber, and caſe-ſhot from the flankers, and many of the Souldiers both ſlain and woun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, inſomuch that it proved a work too hot for the aſſailants: nor was there more ſafety in get<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting off one or two Boats full of men being ſunk by ſhot from the Caſtle; but how badly ſoever the buſineſſe ſucceeded, the Souldiers were not in the leaſt wanting in their duties.</p>
               <p>There was executed at <hi>Towerhill</hi> one that had been a notorious ſtick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler for the Royall party by Sea and Land;<note place="margin">Brown-Buſhell <hi>beheaded at</hi> Tower<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hill.</note> for ſeverall crimes of bloud and treachery acted by him, while he was in the ſervice of the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and after his revolt known by the Name of <hi>Brown Buſhell.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And now once more let us ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance Northward, and obſerve the motions of the two Armies:<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Blackneſse</hi> taken by the Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh.</note> The Engliſh (deſirous to gain upon their adverſaries as much as conſiſted
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:170024:53"/>with policy and their own ſafety) with a commanded party under Col. <hi>Monk,</hi> ſet down before <hi>Black<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſse,</hi> that had much annoyd their Quarters by ſheltring looſe rogues and otherwiſe; After the batteries were made, and ſome ſhot ſpent at it, they deſired Quarter, which (conſidering the ſtrength of the place) was granted, and the place forthwith yeelded. On the other ſide the <hi>Scots</hi> begun to be both powerful and numerous to the eye: For notwithſtanding the many par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and Factions, Strifes, Aemula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, Contentions, Diviſions, Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diviſions, Excommunications, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> they peec't up an agreement (ſuch as it was) to the ſeeming ſatisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of all the diſſenters: And now they joyn againſt the common E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemy, having their greateſt hopes wrapt up in a moſt notable deſign and confederacy, hatcht by the Royall Covenanters of <hi>England</hi>
                  <pb n="97" facs="tcp:170024:53"/>and <hi>Scotland,</hi> whereby a generall riſing in the County of <hi>Lancaſter</hi> and parts adjacent was contrived, who by joyning with a conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble force from <hi>Scotland,</hi> ſhould have been able to confront the greateſt power the Parliament then had, and this plot had its riſe and progreſſe from the Clergy, thoſe foeudatories of Rebellion and trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon; but by Gods Providence was ſeaſonably diſcovered; the Grand Agent hereof was <hi>Thomas Cook</hi> of <hi>Graies Inne</hi> Eſquire, who was ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended and carried before the Councell of State at White-Hall, whence he made his eſcape, but in few daies after was retaken at a Houſe in the Strand; Next diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very was by means of a Ship bound from the North of <hi>Scotland</hi> to the <hi>Iſle of Man,</hi> which by contrary windes was driven into <hi>Ayre,</hi> and there ſecur'd and ſearcht, wherein were found many notable Papers,
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:170024:54"/>giving further light into the buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</p>
               <p>Not long after this a Party of Horſe and Dragoons marched to <hi>Grenock,</hi> near <hi>Dunbarton,</hi> where they ſeiz'd M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Birkenhead</hi> another Agent for the Royall deſigns, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout whom they found ſuch Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, Commiſſions and Inſtructions, that therein their whole plot was diſcovered; Upon which the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament ordered, that a conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble body of Horſe and Foot ſhould march Northward, under the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of Major Generall <hi>Harriſon</hi> both to prevent inſurrections and likewiſe to oppoſe the Enemy, if they ſhould make an inrode by the way of <hi>Carliſle.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>At <hi>London</hi> was under queſtion the moſt eminent actors in and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributors to the plot aforeſaid, <hi>viz.</hi> M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Chriſtopher Love,</hi> Major <hi>Alford,</hi> Maj. <hi>Adams,</hi> Col. <hi>Barton,</hi> M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Black<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more,</hi> M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Caſe,</hi> M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Cauton,</hi> D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Drake,</hi>
                  <pb n="99" facs="tcp:170024:54"/>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Drake,</hi> Capt. <hi>Farr,</hi> M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Gibbons,</hi> M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Haviland,</hi> Major <hi>Huntington,</hi> M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Jenkins,</hi> M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Jaquel,</hi> M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Jackſon,</hi> Lieut. Col. <hi>Jackſon,</hi> Capt. <hi>Muſſey,</hi> M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Nalton,</hi> Capt. <hi>Potter,</hi> M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Robin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon,</hi> M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Sterks,</hi> Col. <hi>Sowton,</hi> Col. <hi>Vaughan,</hi> and others; of all which there ſuffered onely two, <hi>viz.</hi> M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Love,</hi> and M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Gibbons;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                     <hi>Love</hi> and Mr. <hi>Gibbons</hi> executed.</note> Now M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Love</hi> although by many cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumlocutions, ſleights, and evaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, he ſtriv'd to clear himſelf; yet beſides the witneſſes of his own party, that teſtified againſt him, he was everted out of his own Narrative, as alſo out of the ſeverall Petitions preſented by him to the Parliament in his own be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>half, after he was condemn'd; which did but procure him a ſhort reſpit from death: for on the 22. of <hi>Auguſt,</hi> 1651, he with M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Gib<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bons</hi> aforeſaid were beheaded on <hi>Towerhill;</hi> the reſt upon their hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Petitions and acknowledge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:170024:55"/> of their crimes were releaſt and pardoned. And high time it was that ſuch an exemplary piece of juſtice, ſhould be inflicted upon the proud and obdurate Clergy, who till then thought themſelves out of the reach of Magiſtraticall power, and that their Function might cloke their actions; but let them know, that Magiſtracy is an Ordinance of God as well as Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry; for there is no power but of God, and the powers that are are ordained of God.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="100-150" type="part">
               <p>Therefore it would not be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſe, if our Governours in ſome particulars would imitate the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>publique of <hi>Venice:</hi> Firſt, By not admitting Eccleſiaſtical perſons in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to ſecular Councels, becauſe they have relation to another Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, <hi>viz.</hi> Pontificiall. 2. By ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving a ſpeciall care to the Pulpit and the Preſſe, that no Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man from the meaneſt Prieſt to the
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:170024:55"/>Patriarch, dare tamper with the affairs, deſigns or tranſactions of the State: It being too well known (ſaith my Authour) that Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men are the moſt perilous and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicious inſtruments in a State,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Howels</hi> Survey of the Sig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niory of <hi>Venice.</hi>
                  </note> if they miſapply their Talents, to poyſon the hearts of the people, to intoxicate their brains, ſuſcitate them to ſedition and a miſlike of the Government; and they have more power to do this, in regard they have the ſway over the no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleſt part of the creature, the ſoul and intellectualls: therefore if any meedle with State-matters in the Pulpit, they are puniſht in an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary ſevere manner, and this (ſaith he) is alledg'd for one main reaſon why the <hi>Venetian</hi> Repub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique hath kept their Liberties in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>violable; and if it ſhall pleaſe God to put it into the hearts of our Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernours to take the like courſe, no doubt but we ſhall have the like bleſſing.</p>
               <pb n="112" facs="tcp:170024:56"/>
               <p>There hapned much about this time a petty Inſurrection in <hi>Wales,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">A riſing in <hi>Wales.</hi>
                  </note> two or three hundred being got to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether in behalf of the <hi>Scots</hi> King, whom telltale Fame (that hath continuall credence with the fickle multitude) had poſſeſt with plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing (and yet untrue) news of the defeating Gen. <hi>Cromwels</hi> Army, and the advance of the <hi>Scots</hi> into <hi>England,</hi> which proſperous attempt had an event ſuitable to the under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taking, <hi>viv.</hi> confuſion and deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction.</p>
               <p>The Engliſh being now deſirous to put a period to the warre in <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> by gaining a paſſage over the river into <hi>Fife,</hi> for the facilitating their work, and more eaſie tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portation, cauſed ſeverall boats to be made, with which they gave many great Alarms to the Enemy on the other ſide, as alſo to thoſe in <hi>Brunt Iſland,</hi> in order to what they futher intended.</p>
               <pb n="103" facs="tcp:170024:56"/>
               <p>The <hi>Scots</hi> alſo made many infals upon the out-quarters and Gariſons of the Engliſh, wherein they had frequently good ſucceſſe, killing ſome and ſlaying others, having the advantage of the Engliſh by their knowledge of the Countrey, for prevention whereof, orders were given out for drawing off their remoteſt Gariſons, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracting their Quarters, which was done accordingly, and the Army put into a marching poſture for <hi>Fife,</hi> for which purpoſe <hi>Blackneſſe</hi> was made their Magazine; but the Ground not yet affording either Graſſe or Oats, the enterpriſe was further ſuſpended.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Scots</hi> having compleated their Levies to the Number of 15000 Foot and 6000 Horſe, mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched on this ſide <hi>Sterling</hi> to a place called <hi>Torwood,</hi> where they were faced by the Engliſh, but would not be drawn to an Engagement,
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:170024:57"/>yet ſtill lay encamp'd behind bogs, and inacceſſible faſtneſſes, on pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe to delay the Warre: Upon which the Engliſh reſolved to land ſome Forces on <hi>Fife</hi> ſide,<note place="margin">The Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh gain a paſſage o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver into <hi>Fife.</hi>
                  </note> and for that end there was drawn out 1600 Foot, and 4 Troops of Horſe, commanded by Col. <hi>Overton,</hi> who attempted to land at Queens Ferry, which on the 17<hi rend="sup">th</hi> of <hi>July</hi> 1651. with the loſſe of about ſix men was effected, and preſently they fell to intrench themſelves: while this was doing the Lord Gen. <hi>Cromwell</hi> with his Army marcht cloſe up to the Enemy, that in caſe they had marcht towards <hi>Fife,</hi> he might have engaged their rear before they could have reacht <hi>Sterling:</hi> The <hi>Scots</hi> receiving the Alarm the ſame day, forthwith ſent a conſiderable party of Horſe and Foot to the number of 4000 under Sir <hi>John Brown</hi> to drive the Engliſh out of <hi>Fife:</hi> upon which Gen. <hi>Cromwell</hi>
                  <pb n="105" facs="tcp:170024:57"/>ſent Maj. Gen. <hi>Lambert</hi> with two Regiments of Horſe and two of Foot to re-enforce the other party, who in 24 hours were ferryed over and joyned, upon which Col. <hi>Okey</hi> with his Regiment fell in among the Enemy, whereby they were forc't to draw into a Battalia, as did the Engliſh alſo, who were more in number then the Enemy, though to equalize that they had greater advantages of ground. In this poſture they continued facing each other about an hour and half; whereupon the Engliſh reſolved to attempt the Enemy by aſcending the Hill, which being done (after a ſhort diſpute) the <hi>Scots</hi> were ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly routed,<note place="margin">4000 of the <hi>Scots</hi> routed, ſlain and taken.</note> 2000 or thereabouts were ſlain, and 1400 taken Priſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, whereof Sir <hi>John Brown</hi> the Commander in chief was one, with Col. <hi>Buchanan</hi> and many others of quality: Of the Engliſh there was few ſlain, but many wounded: A
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:170024:58"/>further additional ſtrength of horſe and foot were ſent into <hi>Fife,</hi> ſo to ſtrengthen the Engliſh that they might be able to encounter the whole body of the <hi>Scots</hi> Army, if occaſion required.</p>
               <p>Immediately upon this,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Inchigar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vey</hi> Caſtle ſurren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred to the Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh.</note> was ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rendred to the Engliſh the ſtrong Caſtle of <hi>Inchigarvey,</hi> ſcituate on a rock in the midſt of the Fryth, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween <hi>Queens-Ferry</hi> and <hi>North-Ferry,</hi> wherein were 16 pieces of Ordnance.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>July</hi> 27. The whole Engliſh Army appeared before <hi>Brunt-Iſland,</hi> and ſent in a Summons for rendition thereof, unto which the Governour returned a modeſt an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, and the next day accepted a Parley: Commiſſioners on both ſides were choſen, and after ſome debate it vvas agreed, that the ſaid Iſland,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Brunt-Iſland</hi> ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rendred to the Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh.</note> with all the Proviſions, Guns and Shipping of Warre, ſhould be delivered into the hands
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:170024:58"/>of the Engliſh, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and that all the Officers and Souldiers in the ſaid Iſland, ſhould march away with Colours flying, Matches lighted, and Bullet in mouth: This place vvas of much concernment to the Engliſh, and ſerved for a ſtore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſe of all neceſſary ſupplies for the ſupport of their Army.</p>
               <p>Thence the Army marched with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſtay to St. <hi>Johns</hi>-Town, a place of great ſtrength and importance,<note place="margin">S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
                     <hi>Johns</hi>-Town yeelded to the Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh.</note> into vvhich the enemy had newly boated a Regiment of Foot: yet when the Engliſh broke down their ſluces, and let the water out of the Graff, the enemies courage failed them, ſo that it was in ſhort ſpace deliver'd.</p>
               <p>This vvas no ſooner done, but the main body of the Engliſh Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, vvere conſtrained to attend more eminent ſervice, <hi>viz.</hi> the pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuit of the Scots King, who with an Army of about 16000 Horſe
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:170024:59"/>and Foot, had ſlipt into <hi>England</hi> by the vvay of <hi>Carliſle:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The <hi>Scots</hi> enter <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> by the way of <hi>Carliſle.</hi>
                  </note> accordingly moſt of the Infantry vvere boated over to <hi>Lieth,</hi> vvith as much ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedition as could be, and preſently after the Horſe: Orders vvere im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately given to Maj. Gen. <hi>Lam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bert,</hi> to march vvith 3000 Horſe and Dragoons, and (if he could) to get into the rear of the enemy. Maj. Gen. <hi>Harriſon</hi> vvas ordered likewiſe to get into their van, to ſtop them and do vvhat further he thought fit: beſides theſe there was about 16 Regiments of Horſe and Foot vvith Gen. <hi>Cromwell</hi> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on their march after the enemy: And to proſecute the affairs of <hi>Scotland,</hi> Liev. Gen. <hi>Monke</hi> vvas left vvith a party of 7000 Horſe and Foot, vvho ſtraitway took in the ſtrong Town and Caſtle of <hi>Ster<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, Aberdeen, Abernethy, Dundee, Dunotter</hi> Caſtle, <hi>Dunbarton</hi> Caſtle, vvith ſeverall others, ſo that the
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:170024:59"/>whole Realme of <hi>Scotland,</hi> was (af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter a paſſage gain'd into <hi>Fife</hi>) with little or no difficulty ſubdued and made tributary to the Republique of <hi>England.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Scots</hi> Army,<note place="margin">The <hi>Scots</hi> enter the City of <hi>Worceſter,</hi>
                  </note> after many halts and skirmiſhes, long and tae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious marches, vveakned in their bodies and diſtracted in their mindes, decreaſing rather then in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſing, at length put into <hi>Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cester;</hi> whence the King ſent out his Letters mandatory to S<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Thomas Middleton</hi> to raiſe forces for him, and to Col. <hi>Mackworth</hi> Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of <hi>Shrewsbury</hi> to the like pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, as he did to others alſo, but without ſucceſſe: He vvas like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe proclaim'd King of <hi>Great Britain, France</hi> and <hi>Irelrnd,</hi> in moſt places vvhere he came: which blaſt of Honour (like <hi>Jonah</hi>'s Gourd) quickly vaniſht: for alas by this project of theirs, of coming into <hi>England,</hi> they run themſelves into
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:170024:60"/>inevitable danger, as the Poet ſayes,
<q>Decidit in Syllam, qui vult vitare Charybdim.</q> being environed on all ſides with the Militia Forces of the ſeverall Counties of the Nation, beſides Gen. <hi>Cromwels</hi> Army they ſo much dreaded; there was likewiſe a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable body of Horſe and Foot under Maj. Gen. <hi>Lambert</hi> and <hi>Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſon</hi> that attended their motions: Col. <hi>Robert Lilburne</hi> was left in <hi>Lancaſhire</hi> to hinder the Earl of <hi>Derby</hi> from raiſing Forces in thoſe parts, other parties were diſpos'd into ſeverall other places, to hinder the enemy of Proviſion, or ſtop their flight as occaſion ſhould be.</p>
               <p>The Earl of <hi>Derby</hi> being landed (as vvas expected) at <hi>Wyewater</hi> in <hi>Lancaſhire,</hi> with about 300 Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen and others, endeavour'd to raiſe the Country, while the Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh were buſied at <hi>Worceſter,</hi> and
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:170024:60"/>in ſhort ſpace by the acceſſion of Papiſt, Royalliſts and diſcontent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Presbyterians, they encreas'd to the number of 1500: Gen. <hi>Cromwels</hi> Regiment of Foot being then at <hi>Mancheſter,</hi> was appointed to meet Col. <hi>Lilburn</hi> at <hi>Preſton:</hi> To prevent this conjunction,<note place="margin">The Earl of <hi>Derby</hi> routed in <hi>Lancaſhire.</hi>
                  </note> the enemy bent their courſe towards <hi>Mancheſter</hi> to ſurprize the ſaid Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giment; whereupon Col. <hi>Lilburn</hi> aſſay'd to flank the enemy in their march, and by that means to joyn with thoſe Foot; which the enemy perceiv'd and preſt to engage. Now though Col. <hi>Lilburn</hi> was over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matcht with Foot in point of num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, whereby the diſpute proved taedious and difficult, yet in the ſpace of an hour, the enemy was totally routed, many perſons of quality were taken, as Col. <hi>Leg,</hi> Col. <hi>John Robinſon,</hi> Col. <hi>Bayns,</hi> Col. <hi>Gerard,</hi> 4 Lieut. Col. 1 Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jor, 4 Captains, 2 Lieutenants,
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:170024:61"/>20 Gentlemen and Reformadoes, 500 Common Souldiers, with all their baggage, Sumpters, Arms and Ammunition, the Earl of <hi>Derby</hi>'s George, Garter and other robes with badges of the Order, but he himſelf eſcaped and recovered <hi>Worceſter:</hi> There vvere ſlain the Lord <hi>Widrington,</hi> S<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Thomas Til<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſly,</hi> Col. <hi>Matth. Boynton,</hi> S<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liam Throgmorton,</hi> S<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Francis Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muel</hi> with ſome other inferior Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers and about 60 private Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers. Of the Parliaments Party but 10 were ſlain, but many woun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded: For this peece of ſervice Col. <hi>Lilburn</hi> was bountifully rewarded, as he indeed deſerved.</p>
               <p>Gen. <hi>Cromwell</hi> (who by delayes, never contributed to approaching dangers) with his Army came to <hi>Worcester,</hi> before he was either ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected or deſired by his Adverſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries; whenas the whole Army was preſently diſpoſed about the
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:170024:61"/>City, in order to a cloſe begirting thereof.</p>
               <p>The firſt remarkable attempt, was the poſſeſſing a Paſſe upon the <hi>Severne,</hi> at a place called <hi>Upton,</hi> which was done by a party led on by Maj. Gen. <hi>Lambert,</hi> and was preſently made good by Lieut. Gen. <hi>Fleetwoods</hi> Brigade, who marched towards the River <hi>Teame,</hi> over which was made a Bridge of Boats, and another over <hi>Severne</hi> on the Generals ſide; upon which the enemy took the Alarme, and drew out Horſe and Foot to op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe the Lieut. Generals paſſage; to whoſe relief there was comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded over Colonell <hi>Inglesbyes</hi> and Col. <hi>Fairfax</hi> Regiments of Foot, the Generals Lifeguard, and Col. <hi>Hackers</hi> Regiment of Horſe; all which were led on by Gen. <hi>Crom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well</hi> in perſon: then was comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded over likewiſe Col. <hi>Goffs,</hi> and Maj. Gen. <hi>Deans</hi> Regiments, who
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:170024:62"/>ſell to ſcouring the hedges, which the enemy had lined, and beat them from hedge to hedge, and being ſeconded by a freſh ſupply (after about an hours ſharp diſpute) the enemy was forced to give ground and fly to <hi>Powick</hi> bridge, where with about three Regiments more they maintained another hot diſpute, but at length quitted their ground alſo, and ran into <hi>Worceſter,</hi> except ſome that were taken.</p>
               <p>After which (renewing their courage) they drew out what Horſe and Foot they could on the Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rals ſide, thinking moſt of his Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my had been on the other ſide, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king a bold and reſolute ſally, wherby the Generals men were for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced a little to retire; but the ſcales preſently turn'd, and in ſuch ſort that the enemy was totally routed both Horſe and Foot, their Works and Fort-Royall were taken, and their Canon turned upon them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves,
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:170024:62"/>the Town alſo was ſtrait<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way entred and ſack'd;<note place="margin">The <hi>Scots</hi> routed at <hi>Worceſter, Sept.</hi> 3. 5651.</note> moſt of the Scots Infantry were ſlain and taken, but of their Horſe above 3000 eſcap'd, of which Col. <hi>Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton</hi> lying about <hi>Bewdly</hi> with ſome Horſe and Dragoons, took neer up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a thouſand; Col. <hi>Lilburn</hi> with the Gener. Regiment of Foot, met with the Earl of <hi>Derby,</hi> that lately ſo narrowly miſt his hands, with the Earl of <hi>Lauderdaile</hi> and above an hundred perſons of quality more. In this engagement and the gleanings thereof, there were taken Priſoners neer 10000, and about 3000 ſlain: Thoſe of Quality ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, were Duke <hi>Hamilton,</hi> Earl <hi>Lauderdaile,</hi> Earl of <hi>Rothes,</hi> Earl of <hi>Carnwarth,</hi> Earl of <hi>Shrewsbury,</hi> Sir <hi>John Packington,</hi> Sir <hi>Charles Cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ningham,</hi> Sir <hi>Ralph Clare,</hi> Lo. <hi>Spine,</hi> Lord <hi>Sinclare,</hi> Earl of <hi>Cleveland,</hi> Earl of <hi>Derby,</hi> Earl of <hi>Kelly,</hi> Col. <hi>Graves,</hi> M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Richard Fanſhaw</hi> Secre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:170024:63"/>to the Scots King: 6 Col. of Horſe, 13 of Foot, 9 Lieu. Col. of Horſe, 8. of Foot, 6 Majors of Horſe, 13 Maj. of Foot, 37 Capt. of Horſe, 72 Capt. of Foot, 55 Quartermaſters of Horſe, 89 Lieu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenants of Foot; Maj. Gen. <hi>Pitſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cotty,</hi> Maj. Gen. <hi>Montgomery,</hi> the Lieutenant Gen. of the Ordnance, Adjut. Generall of the Foot, the Marſhall, Quartermaſter Generall, &amp; Waggonmaſter Generall: 76 Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nets of Horſe, 99 Enſignes of Foot, 30 of the Kings ſervants, 9 Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, 9 Chirurgions, 158 Colours, the Kings Standard, Coach and Horſes, with other rich goods and his collar of SS. Many Parties were taken beſides in ſeverall other pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, as <hi>Warwickſhire, Shropſhire, Lancaſhire, Cheſhire, Yorkſhire,</hi> &amp;c. inſomuch that few of that great Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy eſcaped, but were either killed or taken. Maj. Gen. <hi>Maſſey</hi> being ſorely wounded, ſurrendred him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:170024:63"/>to the Counteſſe of <hi>Stamford,</hi> and by the Lord <hi>Grey</hi> of <hi>Groby</hi> her Sonne, was ſecur'd and ſent to <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don,</hi> whence in ſhort ſpace he made an eſcape: In another place was ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken Maj. Gen. <hi>Middleton,</hi> and Lieut. Gen. <hi>David Leſley;</hi> ſo that I may ſay, the gleanings of this Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctory, were not much inferior to the harveſt thereof.</p>
               <p>Neer this time, moſt of the No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility and Gentry of <hi>Scotland,</hi> were taken at a place called <hi>Ellet</hi> in that Nation, where they were aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled to propagate the Royall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignes: <hi>viz.</hi> Old Gen. <hi>Leſley,</hi> Earl Marſhall, Lord of <hi>Keith,</hi> Earl of <hi>Craford,</hi> Lord <hi>Ogilby,</hi> Lord <hi>Burgoi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny,</hi> Lord <hi>Huntly,</hi> Lord <hi>Lee,</hi> with many Knights, Gentlemen and Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters: all which were ſoon after ſhipt and ſent for <hi>England.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Such was the fate that attended the Scots and their King, that He who a few dayes before was pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claimed
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:170024:64"/>King of <hi>Great Britain,</hi> had now neither Camp nor Garriſon, nor lodging to flie unto or ſafely to repoſe himſelf in for ſhelter, 500<hi rend="sup">lb</hi> ſterling being offer'd to any that ſhould detect him; which not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding he eſcaped, making a diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſed peregrination through City and Country, till he met with a fit opportunity for his tranſportation into <hi>France,</hi> where he now is. Yet of the great number of his friends, adherents and followers that were taken, none of quality ſuffered but the Earl of <hi>Derby,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Earl of <hi>Derby</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>headed.</note> who was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>headed at <hi>Bolton</hi> in <hi>Lancaſhire,</hi> and Sir <hi>Tim. Fetherſton:</hi> others of leſſe not were executed at <hi>Cheſter, Shrewsbury</hi> and other places.</p>
               <p>Nor did the Royalliſts them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves expect any other or better fortune would attend them in this invaſion then that you have heard; as appears by Duke <hi>Hamiltons</hi> Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to Mr. <hi>Will. Crofts,</hi> taken among
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:170024:64"/>other Papers a few dayes before the fight, the ſumme whereof follows;</p>
               <q>WE are all laughing at the ridicu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſneſſe of our condition,<note place="margin">Duke <hi>Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miltons</hi> Letter.</note> who ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving quit <hi>Scotland,</hi> being ſcarce able to maintain it; yet we graſpe at all, and nothing but all will ſatisfie us, or to loſe all: I confeſſe I cannot tell whether our hopes or fears are greateſt; but we have one ſtout Argument, and that is deſpair, for we muſt now either ſhortly fight or die. All the Rognes have left us, I will not ſay whether for fear or diſloyalty; but allnow with his Majeſty are ſuch as will not diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute his Commands.</q>
               <p>So that you ſee, this undertaking was not the product of a mature and deliberate councell, but of neceſſity and deſperation.</p>
               <p>Soon after this the Parliament took order for reducing the two Iſlands of <hi>Jerſey</hi> and <hi>Man;</hi> that
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:170024:65"/>had been and would ſtill be notable receptacles, for the entertaining all manner of fugitives and diſaffected perſons.</p>
               <p>In order to which buſineſſe, Col. <hi>Hayne</hi> with about 2 Regiments of Foot and 2 Troops of Horſe, on the 14<hi rend="sup">th</hi> of <hi>Octob.</hi> 1651. were ſhipt at <hi>Weymouth</hi> for <hi>Jerſey;</hi> they were in all eighty Veſſels, and ſet ſayl <hi>Octob.</hi> 17. but a ſtorm forced them in again. On the 19<hi rend="sup">th</hi> they ſet ſayl again, and about 12 that night came to an Anchor under <hi>Sarke</hi> Iſland, next morning they bent their courſe towards <hi>Jerſey,</hi> and came to an anchor in S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
                  <hi>Owens</hi> Bay; next day they ſailed and anchored be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
                  <hi>Brelades</hi> Bay, when the ſeas proved ſo rough that the Fleet was ſcattered; notwithſtanding on the 21<hi rend="sup">th</hi> it was reſolved, that an at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt ſhould be made upon the Iſland that night at S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
                  <hi>Owens</hi> Bay, being neceſſitated thereunto for
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:170024:65"/>want of Horſemeat; in few hours after they embark'd their men aboard the ſmall Boats, Gen. <hi>Blake</hi> and all his Officers were very active in this buſineſſe, who about two hours after the flood weighed An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chor, cut ſome of their Cables, hoiſted ſailes and ſtood in for the ſhore, and were ſoon aground on the ſhore ſide, ſome at 3 foot, ſome at 4, 5, 6, 7 foot water; their men preſently leapt out, ſome up to the middle, ſome to the neck, and run aſhore; the enemy playing hard upon them with great and ſmall ſhot, and with their Horſe gave a hot charge; yet after half an hours diſpute, they fled and left behind them 12 Guns and ſome Colours at that place; after which and that their Horſe were landed, they mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched further into the Iſland, and on the 23<hi rend="sup">th</hi> 
                  <hi>Octob.</hi> poſſeſt themſelves of three Forts more with two Guns in each; they marched on further
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:170024:66"/>till they came within ſight of <hi>Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zabeth</hi>-Caſtle, under which was a Fort called S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
                  <hi>Albans</hi> Tower, where was 14 Guns, the ſpeedy reducement whereof was reſolved upon and a Summons ſent in,<note place="margin">The I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſland of <hi>Jerſey</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duc'd.</note> and in two hours time it was delivered up. The next buſineſſe they had to do, was to take in Mount <hi>Orgueil</hi> Caſtle, which upon eaſie termes was alſo ſurrendred: but <hi>Elizabeth</hi> Caſtle being a place of farre great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er ſtrength, was not reduc'd till the middle of <hi>Decemb.</hi> following; the Governour thereof S<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>George Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teret,</hi> had large termes granted both to himſelf and all with him, by reaſon of the marvellous ſtrength and ſcituation thereof, which was ſuch as might have coſt much blood, treaſure and time in the gaining of it.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Octob.</hi> 16<hi rend="sup">th</hi> 1651. Under Colo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nell <hi>Duckenfield</hi> were ſhipt 3 Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of Foot, <hi>viz.</hi> Gen. <hi>Cromwels</hi>
                  <pb n="123" facs="tcp:170024:66"/>Regiment commanded by Lieut. Col. <hi>Worſly,</hi> Maj. Gen. <hi>Deans</hi> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giment, commanded by Lieut. Col. <hi>Mitchell,</hi> and Colonell <hi>Ducken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fields</hi> Regiment, with two Troops of Horſe, theſe were all ſhipt at <hi>Cheſter</hi> and <hi>Liverpool</hi> for the redu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing the <hi>Iſle of Man:</hi> and on <hi>Octob.</hi> 18th. they hoiſted ſayl, but by contrary windes were driven into the Harbour of <hi>Beumorris,</hi> on the 25th. about two in the morning, the wind coming about ſomewhat ſoutherly, with a pretty freſh gale, they ſet ſayl again, and about two or three aclock in the afternoon they had a cleer view of the <hi>Calfe of Man,</hi> Caſtle <hi>Ruſhen, Derby</hi>-Fort, <hi>Douglas</hi>-Fort, and moſt part of the Iſland, as alſo of the Iſlanders, both Horſe and Foot in their ſeverall motions, muſtering up what ſtrength they could: when by a ſudden ſtorm the Fleet was hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred from coming up any thing
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:170024:67"/>neer the ſhore; upon which they ſteer'd their courſe towards the North end of the Iſland, and with no ſmall difficulty fetcht <hi>Ramſey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bay</hi> that night, where they caſt Anchor, and with a ſmall Party fac'd the Iſlanders, yet was there no ſhot exchang'd. <hi>Octob.</hi> 16. came on board an Iſlander, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy'd by the chief of that Iſland, to aſſure the Engliſh they ſhould have no oppoſition in landing, but might ſecurely come under their Forts, which they had taken poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion of for them, and that only two Caſtles held out. <hi>viz.</hi> Caſtle-<hi>Ruſhen</hi> and Caſtle <hi>Peele,</hi> which were kept by the Forces of the Count. of <hi>Derby:</hi> now becauſe he had nothing in writing to confirm what he had ſaid, he was diſtruſted; wherefore Maj. <hi>Fox</hi> was boated into the Iſland, to enquire the truth of what the Iſlander had reported, and forthwith returned vvith the
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:170024:67"/>full confirmation thereof; and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently after ſome came from the Iſland as Commiſſioners, entreat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that their poor Iſland might be preſerved from ſpoyl, and the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants from undoing; by landing only ſome part of a Regiment, or at the moſt but a Regiment; upon which, they vvould bring Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions at a marketable rate to the ſhore,<note place="margin">The Iſle of <hi>Man</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duc'd.</note> to ſupply the vvants of ſuch as ſhould continue on ſhipboard, and would aſſiſt thoſe that were to land, in reducing the Caſtles: which Propoſals vvere in part aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented unto by the Commander in Chief Col. <hi>Duckenfield,</hi> being ſomewhat oblig'd thereto by the civilities of the people. But on the 27th. moſt of the men on ſhipboard were endangered by a long and continued ſtorm, many of the Veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels not being able to ride in the Bay: one ran aſhore and vvas bul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, but the men ſaved, many others
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:170024:68"/>were driven ſeverally up and down; which dangers by ſea and delayes by land, the Caſtles ſtill holding out, being ſenſible of. On the 28th. Horſe and Foot were ordered to come on ſhore, and being poſſeſt of all the Forts in the Iſland, they beſieg'd both the Caſtles of <hi>Peele</hi> and <hi>Ruſhen,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Caſtle <hi>Peele</hi> and <hi>Ruſhen</hi> ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken.</note> in vvhich the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſſe of <hi>Derby</hi> then vvas, both which were preſently ſummoned and brought to very low termes vvith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any bloodſhed; and delivered up to Col. <hi>Duckenfield</hi> for the uſe of the Parliament of <hi>England, Octob.</hi> 26. 1651. Where vvas found ſtore of Ammunition and Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of all-ſorts, and in the Harbor ſome Veſſels alſo vvere taken: Theſe Caſtles vvere of ſuch ſtrength, that if it had pleaſed God the defendants had not been poſſeſt vvith a ſpirit of fear, much blood might have been ſpent in the reducing of them.</p>
               <pb n="127" facs="tcp:170024:68"/>
               <p>In ſhort ſpace after there was ſurrendred to the Parliaments For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Cornet</hi>-Caſtle in <hi>Guernſey</hi> ſurrendred</note> that ſtrong and impregnable hold of <hi>Cornet</hi>-Caſtle in the <hi>Iſle</hi> of <hi>Guernſey.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The next remarkable paſſages of the Affairs of this Nation, was the deceaſe of two of the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments Chieftains, one was Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall <hi>Popham</hi> one of the Admirals of the Engliſh-Fleet, a man of ſingular worth and gallantry; yet his ſhort continuance in that employment, did not ſo much ſhew us what he was, as what he would have been, had it pleaſed the great Diſpoſer of all things to have prolong'd his dayes.</p>
               <p>The other was the never to be forgotten <hi>Henry Ireton</hi> Lord Depu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of <hi>Ireland,</hi> under his Father in Law his Excellency the Lord. Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall <hi>Cromwell,</hi> who ended his dayes ſhortly after the ſiege and ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of <hi>Limrick</hi> in <hi>Ireland:</hi> a man
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:170024:69"/>who for piety, prudence and policy in Civill and Martial affairs, equal'd, if not excel'd the moſt of men: yet was there left behind ſuch worthy Patriots and Champions of their Country, as upon all occaſions have ſtood in the gap of the greateſt dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficulties.</p>
               <p>The Parliament (being now throughly ſenſible of the many de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>layes, miſchiefs and wrongs, for a long time and even now practis'd by the <hi>Hollanders,</hi> both in their Treaties and traffique) ſet forth an Act for encreaſe of Shipping and encouragement of Navigation, which was the moſt pleaſing and advantagious Act to the Merchants and Seamen that could be, and by which the hearts of thoſe rough ſpirited men were more endeared to the Parliaments Intereſt, then by any thing they ever did or could do; the heads whereof were theſe;</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>That no commodity whatſoever of
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:170024:69"/>the growth or Manufacture of</hi> Aſia,<note place="margin">The Act for Navi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation.</note> Africa <hi>or</hi> America, <hi>or any part there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, as well of the Engliſh Plantations as others, ſhall be imported into</hi> Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, Ireland, <hi>or any the territories thereof, in any Ships or Veſſels, but in ſuch only as do truly belong to this Commonwealth or the Plantations thereof, under penalty of the forfeiture of Goods and Veſſels, and of</hi> Europe <hi>the like.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>That no Commodities whatſoever of forregn growth or manufacture, which are to be brought into this Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealth in Ships belonging to the People thereof, ſhall be by them ſhipped from any places, but only from thoſe of the ſaid growth, production or ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nufacture; or from thoſe Ports where the ſaid Commodities can only be, or uſually have been ſhipt for tranſporta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and from none other places.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>That no ſorts of Fiſh, uſually caught by the people of this Nation, nor any Oyl made of Fiſh, nor any whale
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:170024:70"/>Finne or Whalebones, ſhall be impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, as aboveſaid, but only ſuch as ſhall be caught in Veſſels belonging to the people of this Nation, under the former penalty.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>That no kindes of ſalted Fiſh, from the firſt of</hi> Feb. 1653. <hi>ſhall be expor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted out of this Land, in any other ſave Engliſh Veſſels.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Severall other Exceptions and Proviſoes there was in reference to the Commodities of <hi>Eaſt-India,</hi> from the Levant Seas, from the Ports of <hi>Spain</hi> and <hi>Portugall:</hi> This is the ſubſtance of that Act which did ſo exceedingly perplex the ava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritious, greedy and encroaching <hi>Hollander.</hi> Who notwithſtanding ſet on foot another Treaty with the Engliſh, by ſending Ambaſſadors extraordinary, and ſeeing they could not obtain their deſires there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by, they aſſay'd to do it by force and treachery: which machina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, God (in mercy to this poor
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:170024:70"/>Nation) by weak inſtruments, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tected and turned upon their own heads: yet could they have pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cured the calling in of that Act, they would hardly have ſtuck at any other the demands of the Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh; but failing therein, they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to diſpute that ancient and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſtionable Right of the Engliſh Soveraignty in the narrow Seas, by refuſing to ſtrike therein, for which they had the fortune to be alwayes beaten, not thriving in any ſuch contempt or bravado; upon which occaſion began that ſad breach be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the two Republiques, the effects whereof we yet feel and groan under; from which God in his good time will deliver us.</p>
               <p>For in <hi>May</hi> 1652.<note place="margin">The firſt Sea-fight between the Dutch and the Engliſh.</note> 
                  <hi>Van Trump</hi> Admirall of the Dutch-Fleet, with about 42 ſail of Ships, was diſcove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red on the backſide of the <hi>Goodwin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands</hi> by Major <hi>Bourn,</hi> who com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded a ſquadron of the Engliſh
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:170024:71"/>Ships, the Dutch bearing towards <hi>Dover-Road:</hi> upon which the Greyhound Frigot was comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to make ſayl and ſpeak with them, which ſhe did, and then they ſtrook their top-ſayl, demeaned themſelves civilly and ſaid, they came from Admirall <hi>Trump,</hi> with a Meſſage to the Commander in Chief of the Engliſh Fleet: And coming aboard, they ſaluted our Ships, and in order to the ſatisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of our Nation, brought this accompt; That the Northerly windes having blown hard ſeverall dayes, they were forced further Southward then they intended, and having rode for ſome dayes off <hi>Dunkirk,</hi> where they had loſt di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers Anchors and Cables, profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing they intended no injury to the Engliſh Nation: Gen. <hi>Blake</hi> with the reſt of the Engliſh Fleet, was at that time to the Weſtward; but receiving ſpeedy advice of all theſe
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:170024:71"/>paſſages from Major <hi>Bourne,</hi> made what haſte poſſibly he could to ply towards them; and on the 19<hi rend="sup">th</hi> of <hi>May</hi> in the morning he ſaw them at Anchor about <hi>Dover-Roade,</hi> and being within three Leagues of them, they weighed and ſtood to the Eaſtward, where they met with an Expreſſe from the States: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon he haſtned with all the ſayl he could make towards ours, and bore directly up with our Fleet, <hi>Van-Trumpe</hi> being the headmoſt.</p>
               <p>Upon which Gen. <hi>Blake</hi> ſhot three Guns at <hi>Van-trumps</hi> Flag, but without Balls, and <hi>Van-Trumpe</hi> anſwered with a Gun on the averſe ſide of his Ship, ſignifying a diſdain, and in ſtead of ſtriking his top-ſayl, hung out a red Flag, which was the ſignall for his whole Fleet, and gave Gen. <hi>Blake</hi> a broad-ſide; this was the manner of the beginning of that Fight which hath cauſed ſo much trouble to the two Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealths;
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:170024:72"/>the continuance was for about 4 hours, untill night parted them, in which fight one of the Dutch Ships was ſunk, and another of 30 Guns taken, with the Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains of both and about 150 Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoners; of the Engliſh there was about 10 ſlain and 40 wounded: the Engliſh Admirall received much hurt in her Maſts, Sails and Riggin, many ſhot were likewiſe plac'd in her Hull, and the hurt that was done to the reſt of the Fleet was not conſiderable.</p>
               <p>This attempt of the Duth while they were upon a Treaty, did ſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſe the Parliament, that notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding all the addreſſes and over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures of their Ambaſſadours, and the coming over of two more, they could not appeaſe them without ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction for that injury.</p>
               <p>Although in ſeverall Papers put in to the Councell of State they la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boured to excuſe the ſame, alledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:170024:72"/>
                  <hi>That the unhappy Fight between the Ships of both Commonwealths,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logy of the Dutch Ambaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dours for the late affront of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered to the Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh in the <hi>Downs.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>did happen without the Knowledge, and againſt the Wills of the Lords States Generall of the Netherlands, taking God the ſearcher of mens hearts to wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe the ſame: and that by Letters and Meſſages, they were daily aſſur'd of the ſincerity of their ſaid Lords, and that with grief and aſtoniſhment they receiv'd the fatall News of that un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happy raſh action; and thereupon fell into conſultation about a remedy to mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tigate that raw and bloudy wound: and to that end had appointed a ſolemn meeting of all the Provinces, whereby they doubted not (but by Gods favour) ſuch preſent cure for theſe troubles may be wrought, whereby not only the outward cauſe of all further evils, may be taken away, but alſo by an interne comfort, the mindes may be redreſſed and reduced again, to a better hope of the Treaty in hand; and that this thing was moſt earnestly agitated by
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:170024:73"/>their Lords for the common good of both Nations, to ſhun the deteſtable ſhedding of Chriſtian bloud, ſo much deſired by the enemies of both Nations: They therefore crave and beſeech this Honourable Councell, by the pledges of common Religion and Liberty, to ſuffer nothing to be done out of too much heat, that afterwards may prove nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther revocable nor repairable, by too late idle vowes and wiſhes; but that they might without delay receive a kinde Anſwer; which they deſire ſo much the more, becauſe the Ships of their Lords and Shippers, as well in the broad Sea, as in the Ports of this Commonwealth, ſome by force, and ſome by fighting are kept.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Unto which the Parliament re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply'd.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>That calling to minde with what continued demonſtrations of friendſhip,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liaments Anſwer to and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution thereup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</note> 
                  <hi>they have demeaned themſelves to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards their Neighbours of the United Provinces, from the beginning of their
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:170024:73"/>intestine troubles, omitting nothing that might tend to a good correſpon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dency with them, do finde themſelves much ſurpriz'd with the unſutable re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turns that have been made thereunto, and eſpecially at the Acts of Hoſtility lately committed in the very roads of</hi> England, <hi>upon the Ships of this Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealth: Upon conſideration of all which, and of the ſeverall Papers de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered by the Ambaſsadours into the Councell of State, they farther anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed: That as they would be willing to make a charitable construction of the expreſsions in the ſaid Papers, endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouring to repreſent the late Engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Fleets, to have hapned without the Knowledge and againſt the Minde of their Superiors; So when they conſider how diſagreeable to that Profeſsion, the Revolutions and Actions of your State and their Ministers at Sea have been in the midſt of a Treaty offered by themſelves and managed here by their Ambaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dours;
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:170024:74"/>the extraordinary preparations of an hundred and fifty ſaile of Ships, without any viſible occaſion, and the Inſtructions themſelves given by the States to their Commanders at Sea; too much cauſe is found to beleeve, that the Lords the States Generall of the United Provinces, have an Intention by force to uſurp the known Right of</hi> England <hi>in the Seas, to deſtroy the Fleets that are (under God their Walls and Bulwarks,) and thereby to expoſe this Commonwealth to Invaſion at their pleaſure, as by their late Action they have attempted to do: Whereupon they Parliament conceive themſelves obliged to endeavour, with Gods aſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance, as they ſhall have opportunity, to ſeek Reparation of the wrongs al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready ſuffered, and Security that the like be not attempted for the future. Nevertheleſſe with this minde and deſire, that all differences betwixt the Nations may (if poſsibly) be friendly and peaceably compoſed, as God ſhall
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:170024:74"/>open a way by his providence thereun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, and circumſtances ſhall be condu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing, to render ſuch endeavours leſſe dilatory, and more effectuall then thoſe of this kinde heretofore uſually have been.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This ſhort and ſmart anſwer contained yet ſomething in it that tended to a poſſibility of an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commondation;<note place="margin">The Dutch Ambaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dours have audience and depart</note> yet all the ſeverall conferences and debates about this buſineſſe came to nothing, but broke quite off, and in ſhort ſpace after the Ambaſſadours had audi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence in parliament, took their leaves and departed.</p>
               <p>And now theſe two mighty States prepare to offend each other, and accordingly Gen. <hi>Blake</hi> the Engliſh Admirall, with a gallant and reſolute Fleet of Ships, advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces Northward towards the Iſles of <hi>Orkney,</hi> to ſeize upon and hinder all ſuch as they ſhould finde fiſhing on thoſe coaſts; where he took
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:170024:75"/>12 Dutch men of Warre guarding their Buſſes, but moſt of the Buſſes were let go.</p>
               <p>S<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>George Ayſcue</hi> with his Squa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dron of Ships being left to guard the narrow Seas,<note place="margin">The Fight between the Dutch and Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh Fleets neer <hi>Pli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouth.</hi>
                  </note> diſcovered a Fleet of <hi>Flemings</hi> between <hi>Dover</hi> and <hi>Calice,</hi> being about 30; of which 10 were taken and burnt, the reſt ran aſhore on the Coaſts of <hi>France:</hi> Many other prizes were daily brought in (both of the Dutch and French) by the Ships and Frigots of this Commonwealth. Thence Sir <hi>George Ayſcue</hi> with his Fleet ſailed to the Weſtward, to ſeek out the Dutch Fleet, to guard the Seas, and to conduct the Merchantmen that lay at <hi>Plimouth</hi> through the Channel: and being about ſeven or eight Leagues off <hi>Plimouth,</hi> he receiv'd intelligence of the Dutch Fleet, and preſently a Councell of Warre was called, upon which they reſolved to ſtand over for the
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:170024:75"/>Coaſt of <hi>France,</hi> as the moſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable way to meet with them; and the ſame day being the 16 of <hi>Aug.</hi> between one and two in the after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noon, they had ſight of the Dutch Fleet, and preſently made what ſaile they could towards them, to diſcover their number, being about 60 ſaile of Men of Warre, and 30 Merchantmen: the Engliſh were but 38 ſaile, 4 Fireſhips, and 4 Scouts; yet they came up with the enemy about four in the afternoon, and began the fight with much re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution and gallantry; Sir <hi>George</hi> and about 6 other Ships, charging through the whole body of the enemies Fleet, receiv'd much hurt in their Hulls, Maſts, Sails and Rig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging: yet did they tack-about, weather them, and charge them all again, and continued thus en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaged in the body of the enemies Fleet till it was dark night; and had not the reſt of the Engliſh
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:170024:76"/>Captains failed to do their duties, this Dutch Fleet (in all likelihood) had been wholly defeated. In this engagement the Engliſh had ſome ſlain and ſome wounded, but of note they loſt only Capt. <hi>Pack,</hi> whoſe Leg being ſhot off, he died ſoon after of it, who was an honeſt and valiant Seaman: there was wounded Capt. <hi>Liſle</hi> and Capt. <hi>Witheridge:</hi> a Fireſhip of theirs was ſunk, alſo two other Ships of the enemies were ſuppoſed to be ſunk, but what other loſſe they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd an accompt could not be had:<note place="margin">Both Fleets re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire.</note> the darkneſſe of the night put a period to the diſpute, ſo that the Dutch ſtood away for the Coaſts of <hi>France,</hi> and the Engliſh for the Port of <hi>Plimouth,</hi> to repair their Maſts and Rigging, without which they could no further proſecure the enemy.</p>
               <p>During this engagement, Gen. <hi>Blake</hi> came from the Northward
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:170024:76"/>into the Downs, where there fell into his hands about ſix more con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable Dutch Prizes, and ſent ſome Frigots to the Weſtward to reinforce Sir <hi>George Ayſcues</hi> Fleet: Preſently after this Capt. <hi>Penn</hi> with a ſquadron of Ships hovering a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the Coaſts of <hi>France,</hi> ſurprizd 6 Ships more belonging to the Dutch, which had been in the Duke of <hi>Venice</hi> ſervice, and were now re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn'd richly laden, all ſtout Ships of Warre and of great burthen.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sep.</hi> 5. The Engliſh Fleet under Gen. <hi>Blake</hi> riding in the Downs, receiving intelligence of a French Fleet, weighd Anchor and ſtood over for the French Coaſts; about 5 of the clock they deſcry'd them weighting Anchor in <hi>Calice</hi> roade, thinking by that means to eſcape: the night approaching, the Engliſh chaſed them as farre as they durſt for the Sands of <hi>Dunkirk,</hi> took moſt of them, and about midnight gave
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:170024:77"/>over: The Names of thoſe taken were as followes.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The Triton,</hi> commanded by <hi>Che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valier de Verdiel,</hi> a Ship of 31 Guns, in which was <hi>Monſieur Bimulet</hi> Commander in Chief of all the Fleet.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The Shepheard,</hi> commanded by <hi>Chevalier Boymerant</hi> of 29 Guns.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The gift of God,</hi> commanded by <hi>Chevalier de la Charta</hi> of 30 Guns.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The Dutcheſſe,</hi> commanded by <hi>Monſieur de la Roch</hi> of 22 Guns.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The Creſcent,</hi> commanded by <hi>Monſieur de la Viel Dean</hi> of 26 Guns.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The Hunter,</hi> commanded by <hi>Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieur de la Gicleck</hi> of 22 Guns.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The</hi> S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
                  <hi>Lewis,</hi> commanded by <hi>Monſieur de la Gory</hi> of 28 Guns.</p>
               <p>A ſmall Frigot of 8 Guns.</p>
               <p>Six Fireſhips.</p>
               <p>This French Fleet was bound to touch at <hi>Calice,</hi> there to take in Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſions and Men for the Relief of <hi>Dunkirk:</hi> but the Engliſh thus in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tercepting
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:170024:77"/>them, the <hi>Dunkirkers</hi> deſpair'd of any relief, and yeelded it up to the <hi>Spaniards;</hi> the like alſo did <hi>Graveling:</hi> this did in part re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taliate for thoſe great loſſes and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juries the Engliſh had ſuſtained from the French.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sep.</hi> 27. Gen. <hi>Blake</hi> with his Fleet,<note place="margin">The Fight between the Dutch and the Engliſh Fleets, called <hi>The Kentiſhh knock.</hi>
                  </note> diſcovered on the backſide of the <hi>Goodwin Sands,</hi> about 60 ſaile of Dutch men of Warre, under the command of Admirall <hi>De Wit:</hi> on the 28, Gen. <hi>Blake</hi> with his Fleet got under-ſaile and bore in among the enemy, but being upon a Sand called the <hi>Kentiſh Knock</hi> (under which the Dutch placed them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, that the Engliſh might be miſchiev'd if they ſhould endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour the weather-gage,) they found they had not three fathom water, inſomuch that the Generals Ship, <hi>the Soveraign, the Reſolution, the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drew</hi> and others were on ground, but without any harm; they all got
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:170024:78"/>preſently off, fell to the buſineſſe again, and ſtaid by the enemy till night parted: After this diſpute the Dutch abode all night at ſome diſtance to Leeward of the Engliſh, as if they had an intention to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gage again. Next morning <hi>Sep.</hi> 29. at day break, the Dutch Fleet was ſeen about two Leagues Northeaſt of the Engliſh; who (though there was but little winde and various) bore after them all the forenoon, but the wind coming to North and B. Weſt, they could not get up to them: yet ſome of the beſt Frigots were commanded to bear up as neer the Dutch as they could, and to keep them in play till the reſt of the Fleet could get up; and with much ado about three a clock got within ſhot of the enemy, who fearing that by degrees the Engliſh Fleet would get within them,<note place="margin">The Dutch are ſhameful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted.</note> ſet up their main ſailes and ran for it, after whom about 10 Frigots had the
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:170024:78"/>chaſe till ſix a clock that night. Next morning <hi>Sept.</hi> 30. the Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh bore after them again with a freſh gale at S. W. and purſued them untill they had ſight of <hi>Weſt-Gabell</hi> in <hi>Zealand,</hi> and ſaw them run into <hi>Goree.</hi> Hereupon the Engliſh concluded at a Councell of Warre, not to run further upon the Coaſts of <hi>Holland,</hi> as well to avoid the ſhallowes, as becauſe of the want of Proviſion in the Fleet.</p>
               <p>The loſſe that the Dutch appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rently ſuſtain'd was, that three of their Ships were diſabled in the firſt encounter, all their Maſts be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing cut down, others of them loſt their heads, and others their Bolt-ſprit-maſts and Yards, the Dutch rear-Admirall being towed by a Fly-boat of 32 Guns, was boarded by the <hi>None-ſuch</hi> Frigot with 30 men, and the Fly-boat with 30 more, but there being water in the hold, and wanting Maſts and Sails,
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:170024:79"/>he took the Rear-Admirall, the Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain and about 80 men out of them, and left the Veſſels with the dead men floating in the Sea: Of the Engliſh the loſſe was not great, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout 40 being ſlain, and about 40 wounded; in ſuch ſhamefull ſort were the Dutch defeated, who were ſo mighty at Sea, that they were a terrour to the whole Univerſe.</p>
               <p>The fame of this unhappy breach between two ſuch Potent States, quickly ſpread it ſelf into all places, that were any whit eminent for trade or commerce, and the effects thereof were both ſeen and heard in the <hi>Mediterranean</hi> Sea, as well as in the Engliſh Channel, whether the Engliſh had ſent ſeverall Ships of Warre, to ſecure their Merchants from the French Pyrates of <hi>Toulon, Marſiellis, &amp;c.</hi> A ſquadron whereof of 4 ſaile, <hi>viz.</hi> the <hi>Paragon, Phoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nix, Conſtant Warwick</hi> and <hi>Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zabeth</hi> (having under convoy three
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:170024:79"/>Merchants Ships, two from <hi>Scan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>darone,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Four En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh men of Warre are wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted by eleven Dutch men of Warre in the <hi>Straights.</hi>
                  </note> and one from <hi>Smyrna</hi>) met with 11 ſaile of Dutch men of Warre, who preſently came up with the Engliſh and began the engagement, but night came on and parted them: next morning the Dutch began again, and ſound as hot work as can be imagin'd from ſo ſmall a number, two of their main top-maſts being ſhot down, and one of their Ships fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, but afterwards quenched: the Phoenix a ſtout Engliſh Frigot of 45 Guns,<note place="margin">the <hi>Phoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nix</hi> Frigot is taken by the Dutch.</note> was clap'd on board by a heavy Dutch Ship, the men over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>powr'd and the Ship taken. Of this petty ſucceſſe the Dutch excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly boaſted: yet they bought it dearly, and that by their num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, not their valour; the Engliſh not giving out ſo long as they had Men or munition; for the <hi>Paragon</hi> loſt 27 Men, and had about 60 wounded; the <hi>Elizabeth</hi> had but
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:170024:80"/>two barrels of Powder left, ſo hard they ply'd it, and to ſuch ſtreſſe were they put: Yet in deſpight of their Adverſaries, they got ſafe with their Merchants into <hi>Portolongone;</hi> this fight was neer the Iſland of <hi>Corſica.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="150-207" type="part">
               <p>Upon the nick of this breach came into <hi>England</hi> an Ambaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dour from the Queen of <hi>Sweden,</hi> where he ended his life before he effected any thing: another alſo from the King of <hi>Denmarke,</hi> who being a contemporary and confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derate with the States of <hi>Holland,</hi> durſt not but dance after their Pipe, and as ſoon as the ghaſtly wound between the two States began to feſter, he departed the Land.</p>
               <p>About which time the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment (conſidering the condition of the Engliſh Merchants trading into the Eaſt Countrey, whoſe Ships (to avoid the danger of the Dutch men of Warre, then in the
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:170024:80"/>
                  <hi>Sound</hi>) had put themſelves into the protection of the King of <hi>Den<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marke,</hi> but durſt not venture home without a Convoy) ſent a Fleet of 18 men of Warre of good force to fetch them home, being in number 22, and laden with ſuch Commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dities as the Engliſh had ſpeciall occaſion for, and without which they could not proſecute the warre with the <hi>Dutch.</hi> Accordingly, <hi>Sept.</hi> 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>th. they ſet ſaile out of <hi>Yar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouth</hi> roade, and on the 20th. they came to an Anchor within two Leagues of <hi>Elſenore</hi>-Caſtle; whence the Commander in chief ſent a Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to the Governour of <hi>Elſenore,</hi> by the <hi>Greyhound</hi> Frigot, and an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other to the Daniſh Admirall, to deſire them to acquaint the King with their coming, and for what; with a Letter to the Merchants and Maſters of the Engliſh Ships at at <hi>Copenhagen,</hi> to addreſſe them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to the King, for the ſpeedy
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:170024:81"/>releaſe of their Ships, then ſhut up within the <hi>Boomes</hi> and <hi>Copenhagen:</hi> but a mile ſhort of the Caſtle the Ship was ſtopt. Next morning the Captain went up with his Boat, and delivered his Meſſage and Letters, which availed nothing: ſo that another was ſent to the Merchants, and a Meſſenger to the King, but without ſucceſſe; for he could not be admitted to ſpeech with or ſight of him: At length two Lord were ſent to <hi>Elſenore,</hi> unto whom two Engliſh Captains repair'd, and urged the reſtoring the Ships; and inſtead of anſwering to the buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, they asked,<note place="margin">The ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actions between the Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh and King of <hi>Denmarke.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Why their Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſsadour had not audience? Whether they had a Letter from the State of</hi> England <hi>to their King? Why they came ſo boldly upon his Majeſties Streames, and ſo neer his Houſe and Caſtle with ſuch a mighty Fleet, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out three weeks notice beforehand?</hi> All theſe being impertinent to the
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:170024:81"/>buſineſſe, a poſitive anſwer was urged by the Engliſh: and on the 26th. of <hi>Sept.</hi> they received a Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter from the King, <hi>That he would ſecure them for the Merchants as care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully as he had done, but would not deliver them to them:</hi> Whereupon the Merchants and Seamen being deſtitute of all hopes of the releaſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of their Ships, leſt them and came home with this Fleet: who on the 27th of <hi>Sept.</hi> left the <hi>Sound,</hi> and ſteer'd their courſe for <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland,</hi> and on the laſt of <hi>Sept.</hi> the Admirall of the Fleet commanded by Capt. <hi>Ball,</hi> ran on ſhore on the Coaſt of <hi>Shutland,</hi> and was there loſt, but her men ſaved: this Ship carrying the light, it was mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culous that the reſt of the Fleet were not all loſt: this Ship was called the <hi>Antelope,</hi> an excellent Frigot, and carried above 50 braſſe Guns: a little after that they took about 20 Buſſes, a Dutch man of
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:170024:82"/>Warre, and a Freebooter of 20 Guns; and on the 15th of <hi>Octob.</hi> arrived ſafe in <hi>Burlington Bay.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Not long after this an Agent, by Name <hi>Bradſhaw,</hi> was ſent to the King of <hi>Denmarke,</hi> ſo ſee if yet by fair meanes, they could obtain their deſires; but in vain: for he did not only detain the Ships, but at length unladed them and ſold the Goods. Which incivilities towerds thoſe that never injur'd him in the leaſt, but defir'd by all fair means, to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter into Amity with him; may one day (by the good providence of God) be requited and avenged.</p>
               <p>The Hollanders (drunk with rage, and greedy of revenge for thoſe rubs the Engliſh had lately given them, and for the continuall loſſe of their Ships daily ſurpris'd and in great numbers brought into our Channel) uſed their utmoſt care and induſtry in rigging and ſetting forth their Fleet: which
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:170024:82"/>(notwithſtanding the ſeaſon of the year.) they effected; and <hi>Decemb.</hi> 20th. they appeared on the back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide of <hi>Goodwin Sands,</hi> being 90 men of Warre, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o Fireſhips; the Engliſh under Gen. <hi>Blake</hi> were but 42, and not half of them man'd, moſt of the beſt Ships being laid up when there was moſt need of them: which default (without doubt) was cauſed through the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>provident, treacherous, ſiniſter and ſlothfull actings of ſuch as then ſteer'd the helme of this State, whom God (in his due time) will bring to a reckoning for their miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carriages: The Engliſh notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding the paucity of their num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber,<note place="margin">The Dutch &amp; Engliſh engage, and the Engliſh are wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted.</note> reſolved to go out and fight them: and <hi>Nov.</hi> 30th. be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ng fair weather, both Fleets plied to the Weſtward, and about eleven of the clock that day were both en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaged, the Engliſh having got the Weathergage: in this fight half of
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:170024:83"/>the Engliſh Fleet (as ſmall as it was) came not up, pretending want of Men, inſomuch that a few Ships of the Engliſh bore the brunt of that fight with the whole Fleet of the Dutch; the Vanguard and the <hi>Victory</hi> engaging with 20 of the Dutch from firſt to laſt, and yet got cleer of them all. In the evening the <hi>Garland,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The <hi>Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> and <hi>Bonadven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture</hi> are taken.</note> an Engliſh Ship of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove 40 Guns, was boarded by two Dutch Flag-Ships, and after ſhe had blown up her decks, for want of men was taken. The <hi>Bonadven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture</hi> (a Merchants Ship) attempting to relieve the <hi>Garland,</hi> was boarded, yet cleer'd her decks ſeverall times, the Captain whereof being ſlain, the Ship was at length taken: Gen. <hi>Blake</hi> going in the <hi>Triumph</hi> to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve the <hi>Garland,</hi> had his fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>topmaſt ſhot by the board, was twice boarded, and yet got off ſafe, as did all the reſt except the two aforementioned, which though
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:170024:83"/>they fetcht not farre yet dearly bought: two other Ships likewiſe fell into the hands of the Dutch preſently after the Fight, but both Merchants Ships. Gen. <hi>Blake</hi> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on this with his Fleet withdrew into <hi>Lee</hi>-road, to be reinforc't with Ships and Men. This Victory, ſuch as you have heard, made the Dutch greatly rejoyce and inſult; ſuch is the vanity and levity of thoſe which gaze on the meer out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide of things, as they preſent them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves at firſt view: Nay by their Ambaſſadors they made the news thereof to eccho in moſt of the Princes Courts in Chriſtendome: <hi>Mirum autem quantum fama popula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris addidit fabulae.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But the Engliſh like a Bear rob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed of her whelps, and awakned at this ſudden eclipſe of their glory, ſplendour and wonted valour, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>took themſelves to new reſolutions for the quickning out a conſiderable
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:170024:84"/>Fleet, whereby to allay the ſoaring pride of their adverſaries, and to ſtifle thoſe unruly clamours and generall diſcontents of the people every where murmuring and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veighing againſt their Governours, as if they had (by ſecret and clan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſtine deſignes) contrived the ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ine of the Nation by a deſtruction of the Fleet.</p>
               <p>And firſt they took into conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration, what due encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment was fit to be given to Mari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners and Seamen: and ordered,</p>
               <p>That the Wages of every able Seaman, fit for the helme and head, top and yard, ſhould be advanced from 18<hi rend="sup">s</hi> the moneth, to 23<hi rend="sup">s</hi> the moneth, and all the reſt proportio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable.</p>
               <p>That for every Prize they ſhall take, and ſhall be ſo adjudged in the Court of Admiralty, they ſhall have Ten Shillings for every Tun the ſaid Ship ſhall meaſure; and
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:170024:84"/>ſix Pounds ten Shillings four Pence for every peece of Ordnance, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Iron or braſſe, to be ſhared and divided amongſt them propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionably, according to their places and Offices in the Ship: and that they ſhall have all Pillage they ſhall finde upon or above the Gun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deck of any ſuch Prize.</p>
               <p>That they ſhall have ten Pounds a Gun, for every man of Warre they ſhall ſink or deſtroy, by Fire or otherwiſe, to be divided as afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid, with a moneths <hi>gratis</hi> money to all that ſhall voluntarily come in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to their Service within 40 dayes.</p>
               <p>That for ſupplying of neceſſary Proviſions unto ſick and wounded men aboard, there be allowed five Pounds for ſix moneths ſervice for every hundred men. That care be taken upon their diſcharge for the payment of their Tickets and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct money.</p>
               <p>That a convenient houſe be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:170024:85"/>in or neer <hi>Dover, Deale</hi> or <hi>Sandwich,</hi> as an Hoſpitall for the accommodation of ſuch wounded men, as ſhall be there ſet on ſhore. Theſe with ſeverall other branches of the like nature, were printed and publiſhed, to the great ſatisfaction of the Seamen: inſomuch that to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the latter end of <hi>Febr.</hi> 1653, the Engliſh had a brave and reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute Fleet out at Sea; notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding all the care and induſtry of the <hi>Hollanders,</hi> to hinder all Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions from bringing any Pitch, Tar or Maſts into this Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weath.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Febr.</hi> 18th.<note place="margin">The Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh and Dutch Fleets en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gage neer the <hi>Iſle of Wight</hi> and <hi>Portland.</hi>
                  </note> The Dutch Fleet in number about 80, with about 150 Merchantmen from <hi>Roan, Nants</hi> and <hi>Bourdeaux,</hi> were diſcovered between the <hi>Iſle of Wight</hi> and <hi>Port<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land:</hi> and about 8 in the morning, the headmoſt of the Engliſh Fleet came up and engaged them, <hi>viz.</hi> the <hi>Triumph,</hi> where was Gen. <hi>Blake</hi>
                  <pb n="161" facs="tcp:170024:85"/>Gen. <hi>Dean,</hi> with three or four more; the reſt were not able to get up, being to the Leeward: ſo that them few were conſtrained to bear the firſt brunt, holding play with no leſſe then 30 of the Dutch men of Warre, and thus it continued till two a clock in the afternoon; after which about half the Engliſh Fleet came up and engaged the Dutch till the night parted: In this fight the Engliſh loſt none ſave the <hi>Samp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon;</hi> a Dutch Prize, which being made unſerviceable, was ſunk by themſelves, the men being all ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken out and ſaved, which Ship firſt ſunk the enemy that maimed her.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Febr.</hi> 19. The Engliſh made to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the Dutch, and followed them upon the chace a good while, in which dayes ſervice ſome of the enemies Ships were brought by the Lee and deſtroyed.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Febr.</hi> 20. They engaged the Dutch again, and the diſpute grew
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:170024:86"/>hot, inſomuch that the enemy be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to fire out of their ſtern-moſt ports and make away, ſo that di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers of their Merchants Ships fell into the hands of the Engliſh: at evening the Engliſh Fleet being a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>Boloigne</hi> in <hi>France,</hi> and not farre from the ſhore, the wind at <hi>N. N.</hi> weſt, which was bad for them to get to their own ſhore; they endeavoured by haling upon a tack, to get <hi>Dover-Road;</hi> but ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of their Ships, having their Sails and rigging much tattered and torn, they came to an Anchor.</p>
               <p>The Engliſh in this fight took about 50 Merchants, and 9 men of Warre, ſeverall of their men of Warre were likewiſe ſunk by the Engliſh, beſide what the enemy themſelves ſunk that were made unſerviceable, and by Letters out of <hi>France,</hi> it was certified alſo that above 2000 dead bodies of the Dutch were ſeen upon the French
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:170024:86"/>ſhores. Preſently after this hot and terrible fight, there was 1500 taken Priſoners and brought to <hi>London.</hi> Gen. <hi>Blake</hi> was wounded in this engagement, ſeverall other Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manders of the Engliſh, of eminent worth and gallantry, were ſlain and wounded alſo. Now though a particular accompt of the Dutch loſſe could never yet be fully known, yet without all queſtion it was as ſad and dreadfull a loſſe to that State as they ever yet knew, for which let Gods Name alone be magnified: and though I am none of thoſe, <hi>Qui malis gaudeo alienis,</hi> yet ſeeing (that by a kind of fatall neceſſity) the ſtroakes of adverſe fortune muſt fall heavy ſomewhere, we ought with hands lifted up to bleſſe God for our deliverance.</p>
               <p>The Dutch being deeply ſenſible of this loſſe, ſent a Letter to the Parliament of <hi>England,</hi> yet ſigned only by the States of <hi>Holland</hi> and
<pb n="164" facs="tcp:170024:87"/>
                  <hi>West-Frieſland:</hi> in anſwer to which the Parliament a Letter, ſignifying their deſire of a friendly com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliance, for the avoiding the fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſhedding of Chriſtian bloud, but nothing came thereon.</p>
               <p>But leſt the Engliſh ſhould ſurfet with exceſſe of joy for their late Victories over their enemies; God was pleaſed to give them a check, by an unexpected defeat of their Ships in the Levant-Seas, which was as followes.</p>
               <p>The Engliſh (having by a ſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tagem regained the <hi>Phoenix</hi> Frigot from the Dutch as ſhe lay in <hi>Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vorn Mole</hi>) fitted themſelves for another encounter with the Dutch: Capt. <hi>Badiley</hi> with 9 men of War weighed out of <hi>Portolongone,</hi> to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the relief of thoſe other Ships under Capt. <hi>Apleton</hi> that lay in <hi>Levorne Mole</hi>) and for ſeverall moneths had been coop'd up by 22 men of Warre; hereupon the
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:170024:87"/>Engliſh Ships under Capt. <hi>Apleton</hi> weighed out of the <hi>Mole,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh Fleet in the Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant Seas, are again worſted by the Dutch.</note> a little ſooner then they ſhould have done, and were preſently engaged by the whole Fleet of the Dutch, who ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the advantage of the wind, with their Admirall and two other Ships, clapt the <hi>Leopard</hi> aboard, a ſtout Engliſh Ship of above 50 Guns, who bravely maintain'd the fight at leaſt 5 hours againſt them all, till at length being overborne by the number of the enemy ſhe was taken.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Bonadventure,</hi> by a ſhot in her Pouder room, took fire and was blown up.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Peregrine</hi> was engaged with four or five of the Dutch at a time, and having her main-maſt and miſen-maſt ſhot away, and being overpowr'd with number was taken.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Levant-Merchant</hi> was firſt boarded by one of the enemies
<pb n="166" facs="tcp:170024:88"/>Ships of 36 Guns, and (after two hours fight) by another as big, the firſt of which ſunk preſently after; yet was ſhe alſo poſſeſt by the Dutch.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Sampſon</hi> was boarded by young <hi>Trump</hi> Rear Admirall of the Dutch on one ſide, and by a fire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip on the other, ſo that ſhe was quickly fired.</p>
               <p>This was the greateſt loſs the Engliſh have ſuſtain'd from the Dutch ſince the breach, and was done in the ſight of 9 Engliſh men of Warre under Capt. <hi>Badiley,</hi> who (I cannot ſay) would not, but I am ſure did not vouchſafe thoſe ſtout hearts that there periſhed the leaſt aſſiſtance, for which he hath been ſince branded with the infa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous terms of Cowardize, Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſneſs and Treachery; from which imputations it is wiſhed he could clear himſelf, in the ſight of God and men.</p>
               <pb n="167" facs="tcp:170024:88"/>
               <p>The relation wherein this Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealth ſtood with the Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bouring Nations was in this ſort,</p>
               <p>The King of <hi>Portugall</hi> not able to reſiſt ſo powerfull a ſtate as this (having more then enough to do,<note place="margin">The King of <hi>Portu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gall</hi> and the State of <hi>England</hi> conclude a peace.</note> to grapple with the wealthy <hi>Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niard</hi>) ſent over an Ambaſſadour extraordinary with a ſumptuous train of followers to conclude a peace with the Engliſh: who (af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter many conferences, frequent addreſſes, and large offers made) obtain'd the ſame; yet to this day he hath not fully finiſhed his Nego<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiations, ſo as to ſatisfie the Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants for their great loſſes.</p>
               <p>From <hi>France</hi> the Engliſh were courted by two Parties:<note place="margin">A French Agent a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rives at <hi>London.</hi>
                  </note> by an A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent from the King of <hi>France,</hi> deſiring a releaſe of his ſhips taken (as aforeſaid) going to the relief of <hi>Dunkirke,</hi> as alſo that there might be a right underſtanding be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween
<pb n="168" facs="tcp:170024:89"/>the 2 Nations.<note place="margin">4 Depu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties from <hi>Bourdeaux</hi> arive at <hi>London</hi> alſo.</note> And by 4 Deputies from the Prince of <hi>Conde,</hi> craving aid againſt the Cardinall and his creatures, who had ſtraitly beſieged the City of <hi>Bourdeaux:</hi> all which Negotiations were in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>effectuall, for alas the breach was too high between the a Nations to be eaſily cemented.</p>
               <p>Other Nations by Letters and otherwiſe endeavoured to be me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diators and compoſers of thoſe mortall jarres that were between <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Holland;</hi> as the Queen of <hi>Sweden,</hi> the Cantous of <hi>Switzer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> the Imperiall Cities of <hi>Lubeck</hi> and <hi>Hamburgh,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>This was the poſture of the Civil and Military affairs of this Nation, when his Excellency the Lord Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall <hi>Cromwell</hi> (a man as it were by Divine appointment ſet apart for great enterpriſes) perceiving the notorious corruptions, dilatory proceedings, pernicious and arbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary
<pb n="169" facs="tcp:170024:89"/>actings of the Parliament, to perpetuate their ſeſſion, and to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thrall the people (by defrauding and disfranchiſing them of their ancient and undoubted Liberties of equall and ſucceſſive Repreſenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives) entred the Parliament houſe, attended with ſome of his principal Officers, and there delivered cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain reaſons why a period ought to be put to that Parliament; which was preſently done,<note place="margin">The Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament is diſſolved.</note> the Speaker with the reſt of the Members (ſome by force, ſome through fear, and ſome murmuring) departed the Houſe. For which diſaſter no man moved either tongue or hand in their behalf, it being generally be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leev'd, that though the Nation poſſibly might not be better'd by this changed, yet a worſe could not befall it. And thus was this mighty Councell diſſolv'd, their Powers transferr'd into the hands of the Souldiery, and their Names re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proacht
<pb n="170" facs="tcp:170024:90"/>and vilified with the ſcorns and dirigies of the common people, who being well pleaſed with the doing thereof, enquired not into the reaſons or cauſes why it was done. But to ſatisfie the wiſer ſort, and thoſe that were more cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious enquirers into the true and genuine cauſes of things, General <hi>Cromwell</hi> and his Councell of Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers publiſhed a Declaration, the ſubſtance whereof was as follows.</p>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <p>THat after God was pleaſed mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vellouſly to appear for his people,<note place="margin">The De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration of Gen. <hi>Cromwel</hi> and his Councel of Officers</note> in reducing <hi>Ireland</hi> and <hi>Scotland</hi> to ſo great a degree of peace, and <hi>England</hi> to perfect quiet; whereby the Parliament had opportunity to give the people the harveſt of all their la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, bloud and treaſure; and to ſettle a due Liberty in reference to Civil and Spirituall things: whereunto they were obliged by their duty, engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and thoſe great and wonderfull
<pb n="171" facs="tcp:170024:90"/>things God hath wrought for them. But they made ſo little progreſs there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in that it was matter of much grief to the good people of the Land; who thereupon applied themſelves to the Army, expecting redreſſe by their means, who (though unwilling to meddle with the Civil Authority) agreed that ſuch Officers as were Members of Parliament ſhould move them to proceed vigorouſly, in refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming what was amiſs in the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth, and in ſetling it upon a foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of Juſtice and Righteouſneſs, which being done, it was hoped the Parliament would have anſwered their expectations.</p>
                     <p>But finding the contrary, they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newed their deſires by an humble Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tition in <hi>Aug. 1652.</hi> which produc'd no conſiderable effect, nor was any ſuch progreſs made therein, as might imply their reall intentions to accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſh what was petition'd for; but rather an averſneſs to the things them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves,
<pb n="172" facs="tcp:170024:91"/>with much bitterneſs and op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition to the people of God and his Spirit acting in them: in ſo much that the godly Party in Parliament were rendred of no further uſe, then to countenance the ends of a corrupt Party, for effecting their deſires of perpetuating themſelves in the ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pream Government.</p>
                     <p>For obviating theſe evils the Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers of the Army obtained ſeverall meetings with ſome of the Parliament, to conſider what remedy might be ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied to prevent the ſame; but ſuch endeavours proving ineffectuall, it became evident, that this Parliament, through the corruption of ſome, the jealouſie of others, the <hi>non</hi>-attendance of many, would never anſwer thoſe ends which God, his People and the whole Nation expected from them; But that this cauſe which God had ſo greatly bleſſed, muſt needs languiſh under their hands, and by degrees be loſt; and the Lives, Liberties and
<pb n="173" facs="tcp:170024:91"/>Comforts of his people be delivered into their enemies hands.</p>
                     <p>All which being ſadly and ſeriouſly conſidered by the honeſt people of the Nation as well as by the Army, it ſeemed a duty incumbent upon us, who had ſeen ſo much of the power and preſence of God, to conſider of ſome effectuall means whereby to eſtabliſh righteouſneſs and peace in theſe Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</p>
                     <p>And after much debate it was judged neceſsary, that the ſupream Government ſhould be by the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment devolved upon known perſons fearing God and of approved integri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty for a time, as the moſt hopefull way to countenance all Gods people, reform the Law, and adminiſter Juſtice impartially: hoping thereby the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple might forget Monarchy, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand their true intereſt in the ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of ſucceſsive Parliaments; that ſo the Government might be ſetled up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a right Baſis, without hazard to
<pb n="174" facs="tcp:170024:92"/>this glorious cauſe, or neceſsitating to keep up Armies for the defence of the ſame.</p>
                     <p>And being ſtill reſolved to uſe all means poſsible to avoid extraordinary courſes, we prevalied with about <hi>20</hi> Members of Parliament, to give us a conference, with whom we plainly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bated the neceſsity and juſtneſs of our Propoſals: The which found no ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptance, but in ſtead thereof it was offered that the way was to continue ſtill this Parliament, as being that from which we might probably expect all good things. This being vehemently inſiſted on did much confirm us in our apprehenſions; That not any love to a Repreſentative, but the making uſe thereof to recruit, and ſo to perpetuate themſelves, was their aim, in the Act they had then under conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration.</p>
                     <p>For preventing the conſummating whereof, and all the ſad and evil con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequences, which upon the grounds
<pb n="175" facs="tcp:170024:92"/>aforeſaid must have enſued, and where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by at one blow the intereſt of all honeſt men and of this glorious cauſe had been endangered to be laid in the duſt, and theſe Nations imbroyled in new trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, at a time when our enemies a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad are watching all advantages a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst, and ſome of them actually en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaged in Warre with us; we have been neceſsitated (though with much relu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctancy) to put an end to this Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <p>This Declaration and proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of Gen. <hi>Cromwell</hi> and his Councell of Officers, was attended with the conſent of the Generals and all the Captains of the Fleet, as alſo of the Generals and Officers of all the land Forces in <hi>Ireland</hi> and <hi>Scotland.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But leaſt the Magiſtrates, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther publike Miniſters of the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, ſhould be ſtartled at this ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den change, ſo as to ſwerve from
<pb n="176" facs="tcp:170024:93"/>their duties; or others ſhould take occaſion thereby to make diſtur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bances in the Commonwealth, this following Delaration was pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed.</p>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <p>WHereas the Parliament being diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved, Perſons of approved fide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity and honeſty, are (according to the late Declaration of the <hi>22<hi rend="sup">th</hi>
                        </hi> of <hi>April</hi> laſt) to be called from the ſeverall parts of this Commonwealth to the ſupream Authority; and although ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectual proceedings are and have been had for perfecting thoſe reſolutions; yet ſome convenient time being requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red for the aſſembling of thoſe perſons, it hath been found neceſsary for pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venting the miſchiefs and inconve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niences which may ariſe in the mean while to the publike affairs, that a Councell of State be conſtituted, to take care of and intend, the peace, ſafety and preſent management of the affairs of his Commonwealth: which being
<pb n="177" facs="tcp:170024:93"/>ſetled accordingly, the ſame is hereby declared and publiſhed, to the end all perſons may take notice thereof, and in their ſeverall places and ſtations demean themſelves peaceably, giving obedience to the Laws of the Nation as heretofore: in the exerciſe and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtation whereof, as endeavours ſhall be uſed, that no oppreſsion or wrong be done to the people, ſo a ſtrict ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compt will be required, of all ſuch as ſhall do any thing to endanger the publike peace and quiet upon any pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence whatſoever.</p>
                     <closer>
                        <date>
                           <hi>April 30<hi rend="sup">th</hi> 1653.</hi>
                        </date>
                        <signed>O. CROMWELL.</signed>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <p>Theſe Domeſtick revolutions did in ſome meaſure heighten the ſpirits of the Dutch, who thought that ſome eminent diſtractions and commotions (both by ſea and land) would thereupon enſue: but they were much deceived; for the Maritime affairs of theſe Nations (wherein the wo or weal thereof
<pb n="178" facs="tcp:170024:94"/>conſiſted) were carried on with as much dexterity, policy and ſpeed, as the neceſſity and urgency of the occaſion did require.</p>
               <p>Now the Dutch having a great Fleet of Merchants Ships outward bound, durſt not adventure through the Channel; but with a Fleet of about 90 Men of Warre, conducted them by the North of <hi>Scotland</hi> to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the <hi>Sound,</hi> and there met with another Fleet of their Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chant men homewards bound, ſome from <hi>Ruſsia,</hi> ſome from the <hi>Eaſt-Indies,</hi> and ſome from <hi>France:</hi> all which they conveyed home in ſafety, not having met with the Engliſh Fleet either goig or com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: which having done, and hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that the Engliſh Fleet was to the Northwards, they ſet ſail with their Fleet and came into the Downs, where they took two or three ſmall veſſels, and made ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verall ſhot into the Town of <hi>Dover,</hi>
                  <pb n="179" facs="tcp:170024:94"/>with which bravados they greatly delighted themſelves, and boaſted that the Engliſh Fleet was loſt, that Hue and Cry muſt be ſent after them, and ſuch like ſpeeches they vented and vaunted with: when on a ſudden the Engliſh Fleet arri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved from the Northwards, and on the 28th. of <hi>May</hi> came into <hi>Yar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouth</hi> Roade. <hi>June</hi> 1. Being at Anchor in <hi>Sole Bay,</hi> they diſcovered two Dutch galliot Hoyes, to which chace was given till the whole Dutch Fleet was diſcovered, but the weather proving dark they loſt ſight of them. <hi>June</hi> 3.<note place="margin">The Fight between the Dutch and Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh Fleets off the North<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreland.</note> The Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh Fleet (being at Anchor with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the Southhead of the Gober) diſcovered the enemy about two leagues to Leeward, being about 100 ſail: whereupon the Engliſh weighed and made ſail towards them; between 11 and 12 at noon both Fleets were engaged, and for ſome hours the diſpute was ſharp,
<pb n="180" facs="tcp:170024:95"/>inſomuch that about 6 a clock in the evening the enemy bore right away before the winde,<note place="margin">The Dutch are worſted, and many of their Ships ſunk and taken.</note> little more being done that night. Next mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning early, the Engliſh were fair by the Dutch again; but there being little wind, it was noon ere they could engage them, and after four hours diſpute, the Dutch endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured as faſt as they could to get away; but the wind freſhing weſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly, the Engliſh bore in ſo hard among them, that they took 11 Men of Warre, and 2 water-Hoyes, 6 Captains, 1500 Priſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, and ſunk 6 Men of Warre more; the reſt of the Dutch Fleet (if night had not prevented) would probably have been cut off; but darkneſſe coming on, and being near the Flats, and neceſſitated to ſtay and mend their ſails and rig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging, which were much ſhattered and torn, they came to an Anchor about 10 a clock that night. The
<pb n="181" facs="tcp:170024:95"/>loſſe which the Engliſh ſuſtained in this fight, was of Gen. <hi>Dean</hi> one of their Admirals, who with a great ſhot was taken off the firſt daies en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagement, one Capt. they loſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide, they had ſlain at the uttermoſt not above 150 men, and about 240 wounded, but they loſt not one Ship. That which greatly anima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the Engliſh, and diſcouraged the Dutch, was the opportune and ſeaſonable coming in of Gen. <hi>Blake</hi> with about 16 ſail of ſtout Men of Warre. The Dutch having (by the advantage of the night) got in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the <hi>Wielings,</hi> the <hi>Ulye</hi> and the <hi>Texel;</hi> the Engliſh called a Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell of all the Captains of the Fleet, to adviſe what was the moſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venient courſe for improvement of the victory to the beſt advantage: where it was reſolved to make what ſail they could with the whole Fleet towards the <hi>Wielings,</hi> ſo far as with ſafety they might,
<pb n="182" facs="tcp:170024:96"/>and ſo range the Dutch Coaſt till they came to the <hi>Texel,</hi> where they lay for a pretty ſpace of time, ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king Prizes continually more or leſſe, to the wofull prejudice of the Dutch, whoſe Ships could in that while neither go out nor come in, nor get together in any one Port, whereby to unite and get to a head: in which condition I ſhall for the preſent leave them.</p>
               <p>Gen. <hi>Cromwell</hi> and his Councell of Officers having finiſh'd their conſultations and reſolutions about thoſe Perſons to whom the Ligiſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Power of the Nation was to be committed; Warrants were iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſued out to each perſon ſo choſen in the three Nations, to appear at the Councel-Chamber at <hi>White<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hall July</hi> 4<hi rend="sup">th</hi> 1653. a Copy where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of followes:</p>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <p>FOraſmuch as upon the diſſolution of the late Parliament it became neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary,
<pb n="183" facs="tcp:170024:96"/>that the peace, ſafety and good government of this Commonwealth ſhould be provided for; and in order thereunto, divers perſons fearing God, and of approved fidelity and honeſty, are by my ſelf, with the advice of my Councel of Officers, nominated; to whom the great charge and trust of ſo weighty affairs is to be committed. And having good aſſuance of your love to, and courage for God, and the Intereſt of his Cauſe, and the good people of this Commonwealth.</p>
                     <p>I <hi>Oliver Cromwell,</hi> Capt. Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall and Commander in chief of all the Armies and Forces rais'd and to be rais'd within this Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealth, do hereby ſummon and require you (being of the Perſons no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minated) perſonally to be and appear at the Councel-Chamber, commonly known or called by the name of the Councel-Chamber at <hi>Whitehall,</hi> within the City of <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the <hi>4<hi rend="sup">th</hi>
                        </hi> day of <hi>July</hi> next enſuing the
<pb n="184" facs="tcp:170024:97"/>date hereof, and then and there to take upon you the ſaid truſt, unto which you are hereby called and appointed, to ſerve as a Member for the County of <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                           <desc> _____ </desc>
                        </gap> And hereof you are not to fail.</p>
                     <closer>
                        <dateline>Given under my hand and Seal the <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                              <desc> _____ </desc>
                           </gap> 
                           <date> day of <hi>June 1653.</hi>
                           </date>
                        </dateline>
                        <signed>O. CROMWELL.</signed>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <p>
                  <hi>July</hi> 4<hi rend="sup">th</hi> the ſeverall Members met accordingly in the Councel-Chamber, where was the Lord Gen. <hi>Cromwell</hi> and many of his Officers about him, who ſtanding up, made an excellent, uſefull and ſeaſonable Speech unto them; re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counting the many wonderfull mercies of God towards this Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and the continued ſeries of providences by which he had ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared, in carrying on this Cauſe, and bringing affairs into the preſent condition.</p>
               <p>He ſet forth likewiſe the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſe of affairs ſince the famous
<pb n="185" facs="tcp:170024:97"/>victory at <hi>Worceſter,</hi> as alſo the actings of the Army thereupon, after divers applications to the Parliament, and much waiting up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them, with the grounds and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity of their diſſolving the late Parliament, which he declared to be for the preſervation of this Cauſe, and the intereſt of all honeſt men who have been engaged therein.</p>
               <p>He in like manner held forth the cleerneſſe of the Call given to the Members then preſent, to take upon them the ſupream Authority: and from the Scriptures exhorted them to their duties, and encouraged them therein: He further deſired them that a tenderneſſe might be uſed towards all conſcientious per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of what judgement ſoever.</p>
               <p>Which having ended, his Excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency produced an Inſtrument un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der his own hand and Seal, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by he did with the advice of his Officers, devolve and intruſt the
<pb n="186" facs="tcp:170024:98"/>Supream Authority and Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of this Commonwealth, into the hands of the Perſons there met, Who, or any fourty of them, are to be held and acknowledged the Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pream Authority of the Nation; unto whom all perſons within the ſame, and the territories thereunto belonging, are to yeeld obedience and ſubjection. And that they ſit no longer then the 3<hi rend="sup">d</hi> of <hi>Novemb.</hi> 1654. And three moneths before their diſſolution, they were to make choice of other Perſons to ſucceed them, who were not to ſit above a twelvemoneth, and then to take care for a ſucceſſion in Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Which Inſtrument being delivered to the Members, his Lordſhip commended them to God, and with his Officers with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drew. From thence the Members adjourned forthwith to the old Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament houſe, and there ſate <hi>de die in diem.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="187" facs="tcp:170024:98"/>
               <p>About this time <hi>John Lilburne</hi> (of whom I have already made mention) being a few moneths be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore baniſhed the Land, by an Act of the foregoing Parliament, for certain crimes laid to his charge; took occaſion upon this change of Government to come into <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> and caſt himſelf upon his Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency the Lord Gen. <hi>Cromwell,</hi> craving his protection in ſeverall publike addreſſes; who unwilling to interpoſe or meddle with affairs of that nature, left him to the Law: inſomuch that he was committed to <hi>Newgate,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>John Lil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burn</hi> tried at the Seſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions in the <hi>Old-Baily.</hi>
                  </note> and the next Seſſions or Goal-delivery, he was brought to tryall in the <hi>Old-Baily, July</hi> 13. but nothing was done that day, ſave that Councel was aſſigned him ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his demand. <hi>July</hi> 14. he was again brought to the Barre, but refuſed to put in his Plea, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe he might have a copy of his Indictment, which was at length
<pb n="188" facs="tcp:170024:99"/>granted him. <hi>July</hi> 15. he appeared at the Barre again, but little was done that day. <hi>July</hi> 16. he appeared and delivered in divers Exceptions to the Bill of Indictment, which were ſigned by his Councel and received by the Court; which day the Seſſions ended, ſo that the buſineſſe was put off to the next Seſſions. <hi>Aug.</hi> 13. he appeared be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Bench again, and put in an Exception, demanding an Oyer of the Judgement given againſt him in Parliament, as well as of the Act grounded thereupon. <hi>Aug.</hi> 16. he appeared again, the Point argued on both ſides, but nothing more was done that day. <hi>Aug.</hi> 20. he was again brought before the Court, where he joyned iſſue, and pleaded Not guilty; whereupon a Jury was impannel'd, and Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes examined to make good the Charge; as alſo Witneſſes on the behalf of the Priſoner, who in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king
<pb n="189" facs="tcp:170024:99"/>his defence, held the Court ſeverall hours; and in anſwer there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto the Councel for the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealth were alſo heard: The Jury having the Charge, after hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the whole buſineſſe withdrew, and about 12 of the clock that night delivered up their verdict, That they found him Not guilty:<note place="margin">Is quitte <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> by the Jury.</note> whereupon he was ſent back to <hi>Newgate,</hi> and ſoon after was from thence ſent to the Tower, where he yet remains.</p>
               <p>Thus you ſee what endeavours were uſed to rid the Nation of this inconſiderable fellow, by Tyals, Baniſhment, and what not, but hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto in vain! whenas many a gallant Heart, farre tranſcending him in birth and parts, have fallen by the ſword of Juſtice in the twinkling of an eye! But it may be God hath reſerved him to be a greater plague to this Nation, whoſe heart I fear is the ſeed-plot
<pb n="190" facs="tcp:170024:100"/>of ſedition and diviſion: True it is, he is a man of a penetrating judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, quick wit and voluble tongue, bold and confident in all his undertakings: he is likewiſe peeviſh and paſſionate out of mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure; affects popularity, and is of an implacable ſpirit, not to be ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peaſed but with the bloud of his adverſaries: Nor can I deny but ſome of thoſe things he aimed at were honeſt and uſefull for the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, but he ſteer'd not the right courſe to attain thoſe ends.</p>
               <p>The condition of the Engliſh af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs in <hi>Scotland</hi> was now much af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter this ſort; although the Engliſh had got into their poſſeſſion, moſt or all of the ſtrong Towns, Forts and Caſtles in the Lowlands, yet many incurſions were made there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>into by the Highlanders and ſuch like looſe and barbarous people, committing many outrages, ſpoils and cruell murthers upon the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple
<pb n="191" facs="tcp:170024:100"/>and ſouldiers in ſtragling par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties;<note place="margin">The ſtate of <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</hi>
                  </note> and forthwith would betake themſelves to ſuch inacceſſible faſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes, that they could not be pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſued: The like they do yet daily in great numbers, and are headed by <hi>Glencarne, Atholl, Seafort</hi> and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers; the laſt of which was ſo bold as to ſend a Summons to a Ship that lay at Anchor at <hi>Lewis Iſland</hi> (having before ſurprized 7 or 8 men that went aſhore for Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions) which Summons is as fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes.</p>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <head>A Copy of the Summons.</head>
                     <p>BEing incited, not only by Conſcience and Honour, to ſtand firm to the Principles of Loyalty; but alſo diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daining even in rationall intereſt, to ſtoop to ſuch a wavering and ſervile Power as now Ruleth; I have laid hold on thoſe men come aſhore, as pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moving the ſame: Wherefore I ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon you to deliver your Veſſel for his
<pb n="192" facs="tcp:170024:101"/>Majeſties ſervice; and being cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly perſwaded, that all or moſt part of you are with grief of heart imployed in ſuch ſervice; I do aſsure all that will voluntarily ſhun the unneceſſary effuſion of bloud by that ſurrender, ſhall have ſuch fair quarter as is fitting for me to grant, and as your ſeverall conditions do require, and according to your demeanours herein, you may ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect to finde me your Friend accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly.</p>
                     <trailer>For the Captain, Souldiers, Maſter and Mariners of the <hi>Fortune,</hi> Theſe</trailer>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>SEAFORT.</signed>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <p>The affairs of <hi>Ireland</hi> were much after the ſame paſſe:<note place="margin">The ſtate of <hi>Ireland.</hi>
                  </note> for the Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh having reduced all the ſtrong holds of that Country, and ſhipt away moſt of thoſe <hi>Iriſh</hi> Rebels that (according to Proclamation) came in by ſuch a time, for <hi>Spain</hi> and other parts; except ſuch as were found guilty of maſſacre of the Proteſtants at the firſt rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion,
<pb n="193" facs="tcp:170024:101"/>who were in ſeverall places of that Nation tryed, condemned and executed, in great numbers) drave the reſt of the <hi>Iriſh</hi> into the Province of <hi>Conaught,</hi> and fell to approportion out the Land of the other three Provinces, for the ſatisfaction of the Adventurers, and of the arrears of the Souldiery; but are in ſome meaſure ſtill moleſted by the outlaws of that Nation the <hi>Tories,</hi> Coſen-germans to the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient <hi>Picts</hi> and <hi>Redſhanks</hi> of <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> and the <hi>Banditi</hi> in <hi>Italy.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Hollanders</hi> (perceiving that nothing was to be got of the Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh but blowes, and ſenſible of their great loſſes) ſent four Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioners into <hi>England,</hi> to ſet on foot the Treaty again, <hi>viz.</hi> Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieur <hi>Bevering, Newport, Young stall,</hi> and <hi>Vanderparre,</hi> who ſoon after his arrivall departed this life: the reſt purſued their negotiations ſo cloſe, that we are not left altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="194" facs="tcp:170024:102"/>without hopes of an accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modation. Yet did not this Treaty produce either a ceſſation, or any intermiſſion of Arms; but all man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of hoſtility was exerciſed on both ſides, as appeared by another remarkable fight between the two Fleets during the Treaty, which it is like much quickned the ſame, the manner whereof was thus:</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>July</hi> 29. The Engliſh Scouts diſcovered a Dutch Fleet from the <hi>Wielings</hi> of about 95 ſaile of Men of Warre, upon which the Engliſh Fleet made what ſaile they could after them, which the enemy diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning ſtood away; yet by five a clock that evening, ſome of the Engliſh Frigots engaged them, and ſoon after 30 Ships or thereabouts got up and engaged, the reſt of the Fleet being aſtern; thoſe few bear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the whole brunt of the daies fight, till night came and forced both Fleets to retire: the Dutch
<pb n="195" facs="tcp:170024:102"/>were ſo ply'd in this firſt dayes en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagement, that they were diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered to ſend away ſome of their maimed Ships in the night, and with their whole Fleet got by, ſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving to make a conjunction with 25 ſail of ſtout Ships they expected out of the <hi>Texil;</hi> which by plying up towards them (undiſcerned by the Engliſh) they obtained: which conjunction the Engliſh (by reaſon of thick and foul weather) could not hinder by engagement nor o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe.<note place="margin">The Dutch &amp; Engliſh Fleets en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gage.</note> Next morning the Dutch with their new recruits, fell upon the Engliſh Fleet in a gallant po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture, and fought couragiouſly from 5 a clock in the morning till one in the afternoon, both Fleets paſſing through each other with much violence, endeavouring to burn, ſink and deſtroy one another, as if the whole buſineſſe ſhould have been decided by the event of this battell: yet the Dutch never
<pb n="196" facs="tcp:170024:103"/>went off, but with the loſſe of ſome of their Ships which were either ſunk or burnt; The <hi>Garland</hi> a ſtout Man of Warre (which the Dutch had formerly taken from the Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh) was laid aboard by the <hi>Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cester</hi> Frigot and burnt: The <hi>Try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umph</hi> and the <hi>Andrew</hi> were clapt aboard by two or three Dutch fire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips, and receiv'd ſome hurt in their ſails, but were quickly cleer'd of them, by the valour and induſtry of ſome paticular men:<note place="margin">The Dutch are put to flight, and many of their ſhips ſunk.</note> The Dutch ſeeing themſelves in a declining po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture, many of their Ships being ſunk and burnt, and unwilling to abide a further hazard (their ſpirits being daunted) began to bear away with all the ſail they could make, and made directly for the <hi>Texel;</hi> ſo that it was not thought conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient by the Engliſh, to be too bold with the ſhore, not knowing how the wind might take them, many of their Ships being diſabled; but
<pb n="167" facs="tcp:170024:103"/>one or two ſmall Engliſh veſſels kept ſight of them till morning, and ſaw them ſteer into the <hi>Texel</hi> Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bor, Having Boats with lights to ſhew them the way in. Whereupon the Engliſh at a Councel of Warre, reſolved that the whole Fleet ſhould ſet ſail for <hi>Sole-Bay,</hi> to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe of ſuch Ships as were diſabled, as alſo of their wounded men and Priſoners. The loſſe which the Engliſh receiv'd at this fight, was as followes; 300 Men were ſlain outright, whereof 7 Captains, <hi>Graves, Chapman, Taylor, Newman, Criſp, Owen Cox</hi> and Capt. <hi>Peacock:</hi> they had alſo 700 wounded, of which 5 Captains, <hi>Stokes, Seaman, Rous, Holland</hi> and <hi>Cubit.</hi> The par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular loſſe which the Dutch re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd, as to the number and quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of thoſe that were ſlain or woun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, came not to our knowledge: but the viſible loſſe they had, was of about 30 Men of Warre ſunk
<pb n="198" facs="tcp:170024:104"/>and fired; their Renowned Lord Admirall <hi>Van-Trumpe</hi> was ſlain in the midſt of the engagement: and out of the Dutch Ships that lay ſinking in the Sea, the Engliſh took out 6 Captains, and about a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand other Priſoners. This was the ſaddeſt conflict that has hapned between the two Republicks, but a moſt ſeaſonable victory to the Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh, who I hope will not fail to make a good improvement thereof. For this piece of Service, the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament ordered, that God-Chains ſhould be given to Admirall. <hi>Blake</hi> and <hi>Monk,</hi> as a mark of their favour, as alſo to Vice-Admirall <hi>Pen,</hi> and Rear-Admirall <hi>Lawſon;</hi> other Chains were ordered to be given to the other Flag-Captains, and Medals of Silver to the Officers of the Fleet. It was afterwards known by Letters out of <hi>Holland,</hi> that the Dutch loſt about 6000 Men in this engagement.</p>
               <pb n="199" facs="tcp:170024:104"/>
               <p>And now Reader (having brought thee well nigh to the pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riod of my diſcourſe, and hitherto entertain'd thee with the relation of things meerly Civill and Mili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary:) I ſhall (according to my skill) give thee ſome accompt of the ſtate of Religion, for theſe few years laſt paſt, which was ſuch and in ſo many ſhapes, that no one form can be aſſigned thereto: for inſtead of an abſolute conformity in mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of Relgion, there was a gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall nonconformity; Hereſies being daily broached in every corner of the Land, which continually ſprung up like <hi>Hydra's</hi> heads, one upon the neck of another, by which means the mindes of the people became unſetled and ſhaken in the Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of Faith and Doctrine; each particular faction tracing a different track to finde the truth, whenas in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed there is but one way and one truth; the numbers &amp; names where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of
<pb n="200" facs="tcp:170024:105"/>of if I ſhould undertake to give you, I might reckon <hi>ad infinitum:</hi> viz. In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dependents, Anabaptiſts, and thoſe of ſeverall kindes; ſome for Impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition of hands, anointing with Oyl and waſhing of feet; and ſome a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them. Browniſts, Millenaries, Arminians, Socinians, Adamites, Diggers, Seekers, Shakers, Ranters, Enthuſiaſts, Arians, Pelagians, <hi>cum multis aliis:</hi> of all which I ſhall ſay only thus much, <hi>Let them grow to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether till the harveſt, least in pluck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing up the tares, you pull up the wheat alſo.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This Parliament having ſate a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout as many weeks as the other had done years, though in that time (to give them their due) they had made ſeverall laudable Acts, and of great utility and advantage to the people, <hi>viz.</hi> An Act for taking off the Engagement; for taking off Fines from Original Writs and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clarations: for clearing of Publike
<pb n="201" facs="tcp:170024:105"/>Debts, and diſcovery of frauds and concealements due to the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealth: as alſo an Act for Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief of Creditors and poor Priſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, which of all others, was of greater concernment to the Nation then any thing they could do: O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Acts of leſſe moment they made alſo, which I ſhall forbear to mention. Yet in other things of no ſmall conſequence, there appeared ſuch confuſion in their councels, ſuch contrariety in their opinions, ſuch a diſſonancy in their actings, and diſparity in their aimes, that they ſeem'd to be a meer monſter with many heads; inſomuch that it was not expected their power (as then it ſtood) would continue unto the time prefixt.</p>
               <p>For on the 10<hi rend="sup">th</hi> of <hi>Decemb.</hi> 1653. the Parliament (having heard the Report of the Committee,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>That they thought it fitting that Commiſsioners be ſent into all the
<pb n="202" facs="tcp:170024:106"/>Counties, and inabled to eject ſcanda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous and unable Miniſters; and alſo be impowred to ſettle able Miniſters in all void places.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>That ſuch as are or ſhall be approved for publike Preachers of the Goſpel, ſhall have and enjoy ſuch maintenance as is already ſetled by Law.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>That upon hearing and conſidering what hath been offered to the Commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tee touching propriety in Tythes, of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumbents, Rectors, Poſſeſſors of Dona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives or appropriate Tythes; It is the opinion of this Committee, That the ſaid perſons have a Legall propriety in Tythes.)</hi> The Parliament, I ſay, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving ſpent ſeverall daies in debate of this Report, <hi>Decemb.</hi> 10. put the firſt of theſe Reports to the Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion, <hi>viz. Whether the Houſe doth agree with the first Clauſe of this Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port?</hi> which was carried in the Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gative.</p>
               <p>Munday <hi>Decemb.</hi> 12<hi rend="sup">th</hi> ſomewhat early, the Houſe being ſate, a Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman
<pb n="203" facs="tcp:170024:106"/>ſtood up and moved; <hi>That the ſitting of this Parliament, as then conſtituted, would not be for the good of the Commonwealth; and that there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it was requiſite to deliver up unto the Lord Generall</hi> Cromwell <hi>the Powers which they received from him:</hi> This motion being ſeconded by ſeverall other Members, the Houſe roſe, and the Speaker with many Members of the Houſe, departed and went to <hi>Whitehall;</hi> where they (being the greater number of the Members ſitting in Parliament) did by a Writing under their hands,<note place="margin">The Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament diſſolved, <hi>Dec.</hi> 12<hi rend="sup">th</hi> 1653.</note> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigne unto his Excellency their ſaid Powers; and M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Speaker, attended with the Members, did preſent the ſame to his Excellency accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly.</p>
               <p>This was no ſooner done, but (after ſerious conſultation and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate about the emergent occaſions of the Land,) the Lord Generall <hi>Cromwell</hi> was (in the preſence of all
<pb n="204" facs="tcp:170024:107"/>the Judges and Juſtices of the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verall Courts at <hi>Westminſter,</hi> the Barons of the Exchequer, the Kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers of the Liberties of <hi>England,</hi> the Lord Major and Aldermen of the City of <hi>London,</hi> with moſt of the chief Officers of the Army) ſworne Lord Protector of the Commonwealth of <hi>England, Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> and of all the I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlands and Territories thereunto belonging: Severall Articles by which he is to govern the People being then read to him, to the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance whereof, he took a ſolmn Oath in the preſence of them all; the ſumme whereof was,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>That he ſhould call a Parliament every three years. That the firſt ſhould be</hi> Sept. 3<hi rend="sup">d</hi> 1654. <hi>That he ſhould not diſſolve it untill they had ſate five moneths. That whatſoever Bill they ſhould paſſe, if he ſhould not ſigne it in</hi> 20 <hi>dayes, that then it ſhould paſſe without him. That he ſhould have a
<pb n="205" facs="tcp:170024:107"/>Councell of ſelect Perſons to aſsiſt him, nor under</hi> 13, <hi>nor above</hi> 21. <hi>That immediately after his Death, the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell ſhall chooſe another Protector be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they riſe. That no Protector for the future ſhall be Generall of the Army. That the Protector ſhall have power to to make Peace or Warre. That, with the conſent of his Councell, he may make Lawes which ſhall be binding till the next Seſsion of Parliament.</hi> Theſe with many more particulars you may reade at large in the <hi>Form of Government.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Soon after this he was proclaim'd Lord Protector in the <hi>Palace yard</hi> at <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> and by the Lord Major and Aldermen in their Scarlet gowns at the <hi>Royall-Exchange.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Not long after his Highneſſe the Lord Protector was by the City invited to a Feaſt at <hi>Grocers-Hall,</hi> the manner of whoſe reception was as followes.</p>
               <p>He came from <hi>Weſtminster</hi> in a
<pb n="206" facs="tcp:170024:108"/>Chariot drawn with 6 Horſes in gallant equipage; before him rode his Life-Guard with moſt of his chief Officers, and ſome of his Councell; after them rode 2 Pages bareheaded in ſumptuous apparrell; after them about 12 Lackeys with velvet Caps in gray Liveries with ſilk and ſilver fringe; then came his Highneſſe, as aforeſaid, in a Chariot, clad in a dark coloured ſuit and cloak, attended by many of the Nobility in their Coaches with 6 Horſes: At <hi>Templebarre</hi> his High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe was met by the Lord Major and Aldermen, where the Recor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of <hi>London</hi> ſaluted him with a pithy an excellent Speech. His Highneſſe then came out of his Chariot, put on a riding coat im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broidered with gold-lace, and mounted on horſeback, two or three of his horſes of State being there led by: which done, the Lord Major took the City-Sword, and
<pb n="207" facs="tcp:170024:108"/>carried it bareheaded from thence to <hi>Grocers-Hall,</hi> all the way where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of the ſeverall Companies in their Liveries ſate on both ſides the way, in railes ſet up on purpoſe, with Streamers ſticking up to diſtinguiſh each Company. After his High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe had dined and banquet was ended, he conferr'd upon the Lord Major the Honour of Knighthood.</p>
               <p>And now Reader have I brought my Story from the end of one Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchy to the beginning of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: under which (if it pleaſe the wiſe diſpoſer of all things, as well as perſons, to grant us Peace, both at home and abroad) both thou and I may live to ſee happy dayes: and if it ſhall pleaſe God to ſpin out the thred of my life to ſome conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble length, I ſhall afford the world ſome other things of the like nature, but if not I am content to acquieſce in the good will of Him that dwelt in the Buſh, and ſo farewell.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
